<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Infant baptism plainly proved a discourse wherein certain select arguments for infant baptism, formerly syllogyistically handled, are now reviewed, abbreviated, and reduced to a plain method, for the benefit of the unlearned, and persons of weaker capacity / by Joseph Whiston ; with a large epistle to the pious and learned among the anti-pædobaptists, especially the authors of the late confession of their faith.</title>
            <author>Whiston, Joseph, d. 1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1322</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12368390</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12368390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60484</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65671)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60484)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 929:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Infant baptism plainly proved a discourse wherein certain select arguments for infant baptism, formerly syllogyistically handled, are now reviewed, abbreviated, and reduced to a plain method, for the benefit of the unlearned, and persons of weaker capacity / by Joseph Whiston ; with a large epistle to the pious and learned among the anti-pædobaptists, especially the authors of the late confession of their faith.</title>
                  <author>Whiston, Joseph, d. 1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 128 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 128.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Paul Schaffner</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Infant-baptism,</hi> Plainly Proved.</p>
            <p>A DISCOURSE WHEREIN Certain ſelect Arguments for INFANT-BAPTISM, formerly ſyllogiſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, are now reviewed, abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated, and reduced to a plain Method, for the benefit of the Unlearned, and Perſons of weaker Capacity.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOSEPH WHISTON,</hi> With a large Epiſtle to the Pious and Learned among the Anti-paedobaptiſts, eſpecially the Authors of the late Confeſſion of their Faith.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Ye do err, not knowing the Scriptures,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 22.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Quo imperitior Sermo, hoc illuſtrior Ratio eſt.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutius Felix.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He enſuing Sheets are only an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitome of that Plea I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore more largely managed on the behalf of the Covenant-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers; wherein, as thou haſt the main Principles I have proceeded upon, ſo the Strength of thoſe Arguments urged for their eſtabliſhment, in a Method better ſuting ordinary Capacities. The Alterations I have made are only ſuch, as either the Method I have now proceeded in made neceſſary, or I judged uſeful for the more full explication of thoſe Principles, and enforcement of thoſe Arguments, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference whereunto I have ſometimes made conſiderable Additions; which I can with much freedom and cheerfulneſs of Mind put into thine hands, becauſe they now for ſome years have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered themſelves to the ſevereſt Teſt of the most Critical Oppoſers of the Practice pleaded for, who either have utterly declined their Examination, or after the ſtricteſt Examination of them have not been able to produce any juſt exception againſt them. And beſides they are now reduced to ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:60484:3"/>a Method, and clothed in ſuch a Dreſs, as ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects them to thine own Teſt and Examination; thou mayeſt (as I may ſay) ſee with thine own Eyes. Here are no <hi>Majors</hi> or <hi>Minors</hi> to puzzle thy Head withal: but as the Propoſitions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Principles I have proceeded on, are plainly ſet down; ſo their Explications and Proofs are, both in reſpect of Method and Terms uſed, accommodated to thine own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Neither is there any great Strength of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory required to retain the firſt Propoſition, with the Evidence given in thereunto, till thou comeſt to the ſecond; nor to retain that or the ſecond, till thou comeſt to the third: nor any great Acute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, to diſcern the reference that one Propoſition hath to another, nor how the main Concluſion reſults from them all three, as laid together. Yet this muſt be ſaid, it cannot be rationally expected, that a Truth perplexed with ſuch variety of Diſputes, and entangled with ſuch variety of Objections, as this contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for hath been, ſhould immediatly be extricated out of all, and made to appear with that clearneſs, as that it ſhould command the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings of all Men to a ſubmiſſion thereunto, without ſome Diligence uſed, and ſome Prudence exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, both in examining the Principles laid down, with the Evidence given in for their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, their ſubordination and reference the
<pb facs="tcp:60484:3"/>one to the other, and the juſtneſs of inferring and concluding the Truth aſſerted from them all.</p>
            <p>The Method, <hi>Chriſtian Reader,</hi> that I would commend unto thee in examining what is here offered, is the ſame that I formerly adviſed to.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Throughly enquire into, and labour to come to a Reſolution about the Covenant-Intereſt or Federal Holineſs of the Infant-Seed of Believers. For though our Brethren of the Antipaedobaptiſt Perſwaſion ſeem willing to avoid a Conteſt about this, and to think that the main Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and us is about their Baptiſm; yet indeed it is quite otherwiſe. Would they but <hi>(bonâ fide)</hi> own and aſſert their Covenant-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt with us, our Differences would be brought into a much narrower Compaſs than now they are, neither ſhould we look upon theſe Conteſts of ſuch an importance as at preſent we cannot but do. 'Tis their Covenant-Intereſt that we mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for; and whoſoever ſhall grant that, I doubt not but they will be eaſily brought, by the Evidence that is and may be (when neceſſary) produced from the Scriptures for their Baptiſm, if not to Compliance with, yet to ceaſe all further Oppoſition againſt it. 'Tis then their Covenant-Intereſt that I would adviſe thee firſt to enquire into, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to come to a Reſolution about; and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto to ſearch into, and labour to get ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction about the Covenant as at firſt eſtabliſh'd
<pb facs="tcp:60484:4"/>with <hi>Abraham.</hi> When the Apoſtle would eſtabliſh the Doctrine of <hi>Juſtification by Faith without the Works of the Law,</hi> he refers us once and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to the way and manner of <hi>Abraham's</hi> Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, (ſee <hi>Rom. 4. begin. Gal. 3.6.</hi>) plainly ſhewing that God ſet a Pattern in <hi>Abraham,</hi> according to which he would ever after proceed in <hi>juſtifying the ungodly,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks. So in all other things appertaining to the Eſſence and Subſtance of the Covenant, he hath ſet a Pattern in <hi>Abraham,</hi> according unto which he always hath and will deal with all who are taken into the ſame Covenant with him. Hence would we be ſatisfied about the Tenour of the Covenant in regard of its Extent and Latitude, that is, would we know whether it extends to, and takes in Children with their Parents, or be only made with Parents themſelves, put that Queſtion to our ſelves that the Apoſtle doth <hi>Rom. 4.3. What ſaith the Scripture?</hi> that is, In what tenour doth the Scripture declare that the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was made with <hi>Abraham?</hi> And we ſhall evidently find it was made not only perſonally with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but with him and his Seed, that is, his Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins. The evidencing of this is the deſign of my firſt Propoſition. And having found out the true tenour of the Covenant, as at firſt eſtabliſhed with <hi>Abraham,</hi> the <hi>Father of the Faithful.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:4"/>
            <p>Then proceed to enquire how it hath been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, and ſtill is continued to all his Seed, whether of his natural Poſterity, or of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; and thou wilt evidently find, that as it is the Covenant eſtabliſhed with <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is, the Covenant Believers are ſtill under; ſo that it always hath been, and ſtill is continued in the ſame tenour to them all. This my ſecond Propoſition, with the Evidence given thereunto proves (pardon me though I ſay it) againſt all rational Contradiction. And clearly underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and being eſtabliſh'd in the Truth of theſe two firſt Propoſitions, thou mayeſt regularly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the examination of the third. Neither do I much doubt thy ready Compliance with that, and conſequently the Truth contended for. And the truth is, were but what <hi>Mr. Baxter</hi> hath ſaid to prove the Church-Memberſhip of the Infant-Seed of Believers, (an Abbreviation of which is now extant) and what is even here offered for the eſtabliſhing of their Interest in the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Covenant of Grace, from whence their Right to Church-Memberſhip doth ariſe, and the Arguments to prove the Rightfulneſs of their Baptiſm upon ſuppoſition of that their Covenant-Intereſt and Right to Church-Memberſhip, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly and impartially weighed, I cannot but hope this Controverſy would hasten to a Period among all that truly fear God.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:60484:5"/>
            <p>Chriſtian Reader, I thought meet to let thee know, that I have had a curſory view of a late Apology for Anti-paedobaptiſm, put forth by one <hi>Mr. Grantham;</hi> wherein not finding my ſelf at all concerned, nor any thing added beyond what others have ſaid, I judged it needleſs to take any further notice of it. I ſhall only add, Labour to keep a due ſence of the weight and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of this Controverſy as yet managed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thine Hearts; keep in mind the Account thou must ſhortly give to him that is ready to judg the Quick and the Dead; impartially ponder what hath been, and here again is offered for thy ſatisfaction. Pray much: and as thou mayeſt aſſure thy ſelf of a ſhare in his, ſo let him have a ſhare in thy Prayers, who is ſincerely thine in the Service of thy Soul to his power,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 1. l. 20. for <hi>it</hi> read <hi>truth.</hi> Pag. 2. l. 13. for <hi>curioſity</hi> read <hi>curiouſly.</hi> Pag. 21. l. 16. for <hi>him</hi> read <hi>them.</hi> P. 31. l. 17. for <hi>indifferent</hi> read <hi>indefinite.</hi> P. 36. l. 22. for <hi>know</hi> read <hi>now.</hi> and l. ult. for <hi>Seed</hi> read <hi>Houſe.</hi> P. 38. l. 6. for <hi>nor</hi> read <hi>now.</hi> P. 43. l. 10. and <hi>what.</hi> P. 44. l. 14. blot out <hi>ſuch he.</hi> P. 54. l. ult. for <hi>Covenant</hi> read <hi>Command.</hi> P. 55. l. 27. for <hi>had</hi> read <hi>hath.</hi> P. 71. l. 6. for <hi>perſonal</hi> read <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents.</hi> l. 30. blot out <hi>move.</hi> P. 77 l. 7. for <hi>becauſe</hi> read <hi>beſides.</hi> P. 80. l. 18. for <hi>that</hi> read <hi>them.</hi> Pag. 82. l. 19. for <hi>to</hi> read <hi>into.</hi> In the Epiſtle. P. 91. l. 19. blot out <hi>one.</hi> P. 92. l. 29. for <hi>willingly</hi> read <hi>unwittingly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60484:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Introduction. The firſt ſubordinate Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition propoſed, explained, proved by a threefold Conſideration.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>SOlomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The Scorner ſeeketh Wiſdom, but findeth it not; but to him that underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, Knowledge is eaſy,</hi> Prov. 14.6. Or as ſome read the latter Branch, <hi>To him that is prudent, Knowledg is light.</hi> In which Proverb we have a twofold Qualification, neceſſary for Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers after Truth, <hi>viz. Humility</hi> and <hi>Prudence;</hi> the former to their Enjoyment of Divine Aſſiſtance and Teachings, the latter to the right management of the Enquiries made: through the concurrence of both which, their Enquiries will become both eaſy and ſucceſsful. The Uſefulneſs of the latter, only to touch upon that, the ſame wiſe Man ſufficiently implies in another of his ſacred Adagies, where he tells us, <hi>The Heart of the Prudent getteth</hi> (or as ſome read) <hi>poſſeſſeth Knowledg,</hi> Prov. 18.15. Others may ſeek after it, but it is the Prudent that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with the Knowledg of it.</p>
               <p>Not to inſiſt upon the various Reſpects in which Prudence is neceſſary, and ought to be exerciſed in Enquiries made after Truth, ſo as that the Mind may come to be enriched with the Knowledg of it, I ſhall only ſay, That he that is furniſhed with, and hath the Uſe and Exerciſe of ſo much Prudence, as thereby to be directed in a right Entrance upon his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60484:6"/>ſearch, will find himſelf under no ſmall advantage, more regularly and delightfully to proceed in, and at laſt arrive at the deſired Succeſs of the Search the makes; and no where can the Entrance upon the Search after any Truth be made more rightfully, or with more hope of Succeſs, than at the firſt; at leaſt more plain and expreſs Revelations that God hath made thereof unto his Church. <hi>The entrance of thy Word,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>giveth Light,</hi> Pſal. 119.30. Or, <hi>the Door of thy Word.</hi> So the Seventy uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally tranſlate that word. Suppoſe a large Fabrick or Building, furniſhed with variety of Rooms and Appartments, the whole Curioſity framed after the manner of a Labyrinth, each Room having a Clew of Silk or Thread leading thereunto, all meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together at the Door; now as the opening the Door lets in Light, whereby a more general View and Proſpect of the whole may be taken, ſo the ſeveral Clews leading to their reſpective Rooms or Appartments diſcerned; and let a Man take hold of the right Clew, and keep his hold of that, it leads him ſafely through all the Windings and Turnings, to the Room he intends to take up his reſidence in; otherwiſe he is bewildred, and loſeth himſelf. To ſuch a Fabrick or Building we may compare the whole Syſteme of Divine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine contained in the Scriptures, and ſome ſuch Alluſion the Pſalmiſt ſeems to have had in his Eye. Thus, as by the firſt ſupernatural Revelations of Divine Truth, the Door to this glorious Fabrick was opened; ſo they contain ſome (though more dark and obſcure) Notice and Diſcoveries of all the main and fundamental Doctrines of, or apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Covenant of Grace; which if a Man's
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60484:6"/>Underſtanding take hold of, and he follow accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as further Light is gradually vouchſafed, they will be as a Clew whereby he ſhall be ſafely led to a clear Sight and Underſtanding of that Doctrine he is enquiring after, ſo as comfortably to act his Faith, and ſuit his Practice thereunto.</p>
               <p>As for Inſtance, Take it of that Divine Oracle given out to <hi>Adam,</hi> concerning the <hi>Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man breaking the Serpents Head,</hi> and the <hi>Serpents bruiſing his Heel.</hi> As by the giving out of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracle the Door was firſt opened; ſo there is in it a general Comprehenſion of the Sum and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all the Doctrines contained in, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to us by the Scriptures, appertaining to the Eſſence and Subſtance of the Covenant of Grace, and anſwerably it would be of no ſmall advantage unto Men in order to their clear underſtanding of, and eſtabliſhment in many, if not moſt Doctrines appeartaining to the Covenant of Grace, to make a thorow Enquiry into, and get a clear Knowledg of the full Mind of God in that Divine Oracle. This might eaſily be made to appear in ſundry In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; but to wave all others, let me only inſtance in that Doctrine I have been, and ſtill am pleading for, <hi>viz. Concerning the Covenant-Intereſt and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of the Infant-ſeed of Believers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That God in this Oracle did not altogether ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurely intimate his Will concerning the Infant-Seed of his People, hath been ſhewed by another Hand. And ſhould I have begun my Enquiries here, it had neither been impertinent nor unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable: but becauſe the Light held forth in this firſt Oracle for the diſcovery of the Mind and Will of God about the Doctrine pleaded for, is (as muſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60484:7"/>be granted) but dim and obſcure, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hardly diſcernable by ordinary Capacities, I have rather choſen to enter upon my Enquiries at the Eſtabliſhment of the Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> an Account whereof we have in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And I have the rather entred upon my Enquiries here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Covenant was then entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> not only as perſonally conſidered, but as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all the Faithful that ſhould ſucceed in all after Ages; and that for an everlaſting Covenant, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure invariable as to the Eſſence and Subſtance of it throughout all Generations, ſo long as <hi>Abraham</hi> ſhould have a Seed upon the Earth. And entring upon our Enquiries here, we ſhall immediatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern ſuch evident Notices of the Mind and Will of God concerning the Infant-Seed of his People, as upon which our Underſtandings taking hold, and we being guided by the further Manifeſtations, that God from time to time, till the <hi>ſealing up of the Viſion,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks, hath made of his Mind and Will concerning them, we ſhall, as by a ſafe Clew, be led to ſuch a clear Inſight into, and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the Agreeableneſs of that Practice we inquire after, to the Mind and Will of God, as we may comfortably acquieſce and proceed on therein.</p>
               <p>For the clearing up of which, let a threefold Propoſition, with that Evidence the Scriptures both of the Old and New Teſtament give unto each of them, be carefully attended to.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60484:7"/>
               <list>
                  <label>Prop. I.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That when God at the firſt Eſtabliſhment of his Covenant with</hi> Abraham, <hi>promiſed to be a God to him, and to his Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; he in that Term [Seed] intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his natural Children, immediatly proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from his own Loins.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <label>Prop. II.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That this grand Promiſe of the Covenant is continued to New-Teſtament Believers, in the ſame Extent and Latitude in which it was at firſt given to</hi> Abraham.</item>
                  <label>Prop. III.</label>
                  <item>
                     <hi>That all thoſe that are under, or are the actual Subject of that grand Promiſe of the Covenant, are the due Subject of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Suppoſing the Truth of theſe three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, none can with the leaſt ſhew of Reaſon que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the Agreeableneſs of that Practice of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants Baptiſm (the Practice enquired after, and by us contended for) to the Mind and Will of our Lord Chriſt. To begin with the firſt, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="proposition">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60484:8"/>
                  <head>Prop. I.</head>
                  <q>When God at the firſt Eſtabliſhment of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with <hi>Abraham,</hi> promiſed to be a God to him, and to his Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations; be by that Term [Seed] firſtly and immediatly intended his natural Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and that as immediatly proceeding from his own Loins.</q>
                  <p>For the right underſtanding of this Propoſition, and preventing all Miſtakes about it, I readily grant, yea poſitively affirm, that together with his natural Children, his Spiritual Seed, <hi>viz.</hi> true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, whether living under the Old or New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Adminiſtration, were included, and as taken of his natural Seed. I do not ſay, that his Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins were <hi>only,</hi> but this I ſay, they were <hi>firſtly</hi> and <hi>immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> intended. I readily grant, the Promiſe had a reſpect unto, and did include all the natural <hi>Jews,</hi> yea, even thoſe yet in being. Yet this muſt be carefully obſerved, That though in this Term <hi>[Seed]</hi> God intended and had reſpect to all <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s natural Poſterity, as well as his Children im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly proceeding from his own Loins; yet he did not intend, nor had reſpect to both as falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one and the ſame Notion had Conſideration. As for his Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, he intended and had reſpect to them, as ſeverally and particularly conſidered; that is, he intended and had reſpect to each of them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60484:8"/>as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and his Children by <hi>Keturah,</hi> as well as <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but as for his Poſterity, mediately proceeding from him, as all the <hi>Jews</hi> in following Ages, God intended and had reſpect to them in this Promiſe only as more generally conſidered; that is, he intended and had reſpect to them only in general, as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, but he intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them not, nor had reſpect to them as ſeverally and particularly conſidered. Hence no one of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>'s Poſterity, beyond thoſe that did immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly proceed from his own Loins, had this Promiſe appertaining to them, as ſingularly or particularly conſidered meerly as of his natural Seed; but whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever among them were in Covenant, or had the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe appertaining to them, they were either ſuch as had <hi>perſonally</hi> taken hold of the <hi>Covenant</hi> themſelves, or were the natural Children of thoſe who had ſo done. So that for the underſtanding the full Mind of God in that grand Promiſe, we muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh of this Term [Seed], or of this Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to whom the Promiſe was made, as thus; <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed is either Natural, or Spiritual. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, take it of his Natural Seed, ſo they were ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as proceeded immediatly from his own Loins, or ſuch as proceeded from thoſe who origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally deſcended from him, and were on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be reckoned as of his Poſterity. Now take the Promiſe as reſpecting both <hi>Abraham</hi>'s na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Seed immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, and alſo his Spiritual Seed; ſo it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of, and had reſpect to each of them in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular: But take it as reſpecting his natural Seed, mediatly deſcending from him in after Ages; ſo it intended and had reſpect to them only in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60484:9"/>but did not intend, nor had reſpect to any ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken apart and ſingly by themſelves. As for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, take the Promiſe as reſpecting <hi>Abraham</hi>'s immediate Children; ſo it intended and had reſpect to <hi>Iſhmael</hi> as well as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and to each of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren by <hi>Keturah</hi> as well as either <hi>Iſhmael</hi> or <hi>Iſaac;</hi> but take it as reſpecting his Poſterity in after Ages, ſuppoſe <hi>Jacob,</hi> or any of his Children in Ages at a greater diſtance from him, ſuppoſe <hi>Moſes, David,</hi> or the like; ſo it did not intend them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, only had a more general reſpect unto them, as of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, but had no other reſpect to them than it had to any other of his Poſterity, that were or are alike deſcended from him with them. But now this, I ſay, however this Term <hi>[Seed]</hi> is to be underſtood, yet <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, or Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, were firſtly intended, as the immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and next Subjects of the Promiſe with <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf. Yet further for the fuller clearing up the Mind of God in this Promiſe, and that our Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to the main concluſion may be more firmly laid, Two things muſt be carefully obſerved and remembred.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That as this promiſe had a reſpect to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s whole Seed, according as is before opened, ſo it was made to them in their reſpective Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that is, to them and their Seed, that is, their natural Children immediatly proceeding from their own Loins.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That as it reſpected all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, and his Spiritual Seed, with their reſpective Children imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly proceeding from their own Loins, as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60484:9"/>and particularly conſidered; ſo it was made only conditionally: it did not ſecure the Good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it abſolutely, let them live how they would; but it did ſuppoſe, and indiſpenſibly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, That as the natural Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo the natural Children of all his Seed, as grown up to years of Maturity, ſhould perſonally take hold of the Covenant themſelves, as perform the Conditions of it in their own Perſons; ſo that his Spiritual Seed ſhould continue in that way of Faith and Holineſs they were entered into, in order to their reſpective enjoyment of the Good promiſed.</p>
                  <p>But to come to the Proof of this firſt Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>That</hi> Abraham's <hi>natural Seed, immediatly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from his own Loins, were intended in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe as the firſt and next Subjects of it,</hi> is ſo evident, that it ſeems impoſſible that any pretending Sobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety ſhould deny it. For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. 'Tis undeniable from the very Letter of the Promiſe, <hi>I will,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>be a God to thee, and to thy Seed.</hi> Now this Term [Seed] in the firſt and moſt proper Signification of it, muſt needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend his natural Children. And had not the Holy-Ghoſt himſelf ſhewed us, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was to be the Father of a Spiritual Seed, and that this Seed was included with his natural, all Men muſt have rationally underſtood it of his natural Seed only, and it had been the higheſt preſumption to have applied it to any other. And though the Holy-Ghoſt hath ſhewed us, that <hi>Abraham</hi> was to have a Spiritual Seed, and that that Seed was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; yet for any to exclude his natural Seed, when they have no warrant from Scripture ſo to do, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of no ſmall Preſumption. It is a known Rule
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60484:10"/>for the Interpretation of Scripture, that when a Word that admits of various Interpretations, and is applicable to various things, is put abſolutely, it muſt at leaſt firſtly and primarily be underſtood according to its moſt proper Intent and Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Hence for any to underſtand this Term <hi>[Seed]</hi> in this Promiſe of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual Seed, to the excluding of his Natural Seed, when they have no warrant from Scripture ſo to do, is unreaſonable and abſurd. And as it muſt moſt properly ſignify his natural Seed, ſo it cannot without the greateſt affront to common Speech, and all Rules of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, be underſtood of his Poſterity in after Ages, to the excluding of his natural Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins. so that as for any to have underſtood this Promiſe of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual Seed, had not the Scripture warranted them ſo to do, had been Preſumption: So to underſtand it of them to the excluding his natural Seed, when there is no warrant ſo to do, is unreaſonable: And to underſtand it of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Poſterity, to the excluding his Children de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended immediatly from his own Loins, is alike preſumptuous, unreaſonable, and abſurd, with either of the former. And hence, would but the contrary-minded keep to the Letter of Scripture, which ſometimes they ſtand ſo much upon, a good Foundation would be laid for the ending of this Controverſy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Children were firſtly and immediatly intended in this Promiſe by this Term <hi>[Seed],</hi> is evident from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Token of the Covenant (wherein this Promiſe is one ſpecial Article on God's part) and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60484:10"/>that under that very Notion, <hi>viz.</hi> as the <hi>Token of the Covenant to them.</hi> And this alſo according to the expreſs Will and Appointment of God Himſelf, that God did appoint <hi>Abraham</hi> to apply the Token of the Covenant, and that under that very Notion and Conſideration, as the <hi>Token of the Covenant,</hi> to his natural Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, and that to all of them, without any limitation or exception of the one or the other, is in ſo many words expreſly declared, in that <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9, 10, 11. In <hi>ver.</hi> 9. the Command is given in more general Terms, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant;</hi> and what he intended by <hi>Covenant</hi> in this <hi>9th verſe,</hi> he explains in the <hi>10th, viz.</hi> the <hi>Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> which under the Firſt-Teſtament Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is expreſly declared to be <hi>Circumciſion; Every Man-child among you ſhall be circumciſed.</hi> And that God appointed and enjoyned it under this Notion, as the Token of the Covenant, is evident, in that God tells them expreſly, it ſhould be the <hi>Token of the Covenant between him and them.</hi> And that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> did apply this Token of the Covenant to all his natural Seed, immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, and that as the Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, is undoubted; 'tis expreſly declared both of <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Gen. 17.13, — 21. Gen. 4.8. Though the Circumciſion of his Children by <hi>Ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turah</hi> is not mentioned, yet that they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed cannot be queſtioned; ſeeing the Circumciſion of ſome others, as of <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Sons, who yet paſt all doubt were circumciſed, is not mentioned. The Command of God to circumciſe them, (conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the Teſtimony that God Himſelf gives of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Faithfulneſs) as alſo his circumnciſing his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60484:11"/>Servants, (who were more remote from him than his own Children) ſufficiently aſſure us that they were circumciſed, though their Circumciſion be not mentioned in the Story. And to ſuppoſe that he ſhould apply the Token of the Covenant under any other Notion than as the Token of it, ſeeing under that Notion it was commanded, would be unreaſonable and abſurd. Now <hi>Abraham</hi>'s apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Token of the Covenant, wherein this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe was a ſpecial Article on God's part, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that very Notion, puts it paſt all ſcruple, that by [<hi>Seed</hi>] in the Promiſe, his natural Seed, and that as immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, were intended; otherwiſe the Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and that under that very Notion as the <hi>Token of it,</hi> would, and that according to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of God Himſelf, have been applied to ſome utterly unintereſted in the Covenant, which is moſt unreaſonable to imagine; yea, then God ſhould have ſpoken that which had been utterly falſe, to ſay of Circumciſion, it is the <hi>Token of my Covenant between me and you,</hi> in caſe any to whom it was applied had not been in Covenant, (which in caſe this Promiſe took them not in, they had not been) had been utterly falſe: ſo that to imagine God ſhould appoint <hi>Abraham</hi> to apply the Token of the Covenant, and that as the Token of it, to any unintereſted in it, would be to imagine him not only guilty of Irrationality, but Falſhood. Hence nothing can be more evident, than that they were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, that were firſtly and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly intended in that Promiſe.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. This might be further evidenced, were it at all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60484:11"/>neceſſary, by inſtancing in ſuch of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Children, as upon ſuppoſition of whoſe being intended in this Promiſe, it will undeniably follow, that all his immediate Children were intended in it. And proving that they were indeed intended, thus we might inſtance in <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael;</hi> that they two were intended in this Promiſe, is evident from Scripture. As for <hi>Iſaac,</hi> that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.12. expounded by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7, 8. fully declares it, hence he is ſaid to be an <hi>Heir</hi> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> having reſpect to this very Promiſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9. And as for <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> the Apoſtle puts it out of doubt, that he was intended in this Promiſe, when he tells us, that upon his perſecuting <hi>Iſaac</hi> he was caſt out, <hi>Ga.</hi> 4. latter end. Now he could not have been caſt out of Covenant, had he not been before in it; and that he was not only caſt out of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Family, but together therewith out of Covenant, is evident, as other ways, ſo from <hi>Abraham</hi>'s grief for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>Now if thoſe two were intended in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, it will undeniably follow, that all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Children were alike intended in it. We ſee the Promiſe is made in univerſal Terms, not excepting any of his Seed in particular. And theſe two being evidently intended, there is no reaſon imaginable why any of his other Children ſhould be excluded.</p>
                  <p>From the whole of what hath been ſaid, the Truth of this firſt Propoſition appears paſt all ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Contradiction. Whence ſuppoſing this Covenant mentioned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. be the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace under which Believers now are;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60484:12"/>and that this Promiſe reſpecting the Seed, be of the Eſſence and Subſtance of the Covenant, of both which more hereafter. We have gained thus much, <hi>viz.</hi> That at the firſt Eſtabliſhment of it, the firſt Perſon, <hi>viz. Abraham,</hi> with whom it was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, and that as the Father of all that ſhould have after admiſſion into it, had his natural Seed or Children proceeding from his own Loins taken into the Covenant with himſelf; which how fair a Foundation it lays to our general Concluſion, is plain to all of a competent underſtanding. And the Evidence given in to this firſt Propoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo full and clear, and the Objections made againſt it being ſo inconſiderable; or if any thing may ſeem to have any weight in it, it will be met with afterward, I ſhall not interrupt the Order with the recital of them; if any Scruple ariſe in the Minds of any, they may find Satisfaction in my firſt Book, <hi>chap.</hi> 3. But to proceed to the ſecond Propoſition.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60484:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond ſubordinate Propoſition propounded, briefly explained, confirmed, Firſt, from the expreſs Letter of that Promiſe, <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> The true Sence of that Promiſe ſtated, and confirmed by a threefold Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Secondly, by ſeveral Promiſes and Prophecies, relating to New-Teſtament Times.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="2" type="proposition">
                  <head>Prop. II.</head>
                  <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat this grand Promiſe of the Covenant is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to New-Teſtament-Believers in the ſame Extent and Latitude in which it was at firſt gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Abraham. Or take it thus,</hi> This Promiſe always hath been, and ſtill is continued to all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, in the ſame Extent and Latitude, in which it was at firſt given to <hi>Abraham</hi> their Father.</q>
                  <p>Look in what Sence it is to be underſtood as made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the ſame Sence it is to be underſtood as continued to his Seed, or to thoſe whoever they were or are, that were or are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in this Term [<hi>Seed</hi>], and conſequently to New-Teſtament-Believers, they being undoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intended in it. Plainly thus, as God in this Promiſe, as at firſt made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> had a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular reſpect to all his Children, immediatly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60484:13"/>proceeding from his own Loins, and only a more general reſpect to all his Poſterity, mediatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from him; and anſwerably each of his Children immediatly proceeding from him, had an actual Intereſt in the Promiſe, were in the Covenant, and had a right to the Sign and Token of it; whereas the reſt of his Poſterity, though God had a more general reſpect to them, yet none of them had an actual Right to the Promiſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were they in Covenant as particularly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, nor could have the Token of the Covenant duly applied unto them: So now in this Promiſe, as continued to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, whether of the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> God always had, and ſtill hath a particular reſpect to all their Children immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proceeding from their own Loins, and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably each one of them in particular are under the Promiſe, within the Covenant, and have a right to the Token of it; but as for their mediate Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to God always had and ſtill hath a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reſpect to them; yet none of them have an actual Intereſt in the Promiſe, neither can they rightfully have the Token of it applied unto them.</p>
                  <p>And if it be ſaid, In caſe God had only a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reſpect to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, mediatly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from him, by virtue of which reſpect none of them were actually in Covenant, nor had a right to the Sign and Token; how came it to paſs that the Covenant was continued for ſo many Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions amongſt the Jews, and they had this Promiſe of God's being a God to them continued ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from one Generation to another unto them?</p>
                  <p>I anſwer, to touch upon this by the way, it was thus: Firſt God enters the Covenant with <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:60484:13"/>and therein promiſes not only to be a God to him in his own Perſon, but to be a God to his Seed, that is, as before proved, his natural Children, immediatly proceeding from his own Loins. Theſe Children, as in their Infancy, were under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, as they were naturally deſcended from him, and they growing up to years of Maturity, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them as took hold of the Covenant had now the Promiſe continued to them in the ſame extent and latitude it was given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> it is now to them, and their Children immediatly proceeding from their own Loins. Theſe Children again, during their Infant-ſtate were under the Promiſe, as deſcending from ſuch believing Parents; and they again growing up to years of Maturity, ſo many of them as took hold of the Covenant had the Promiſe continued to them, in the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in which it was given to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and their immediate Parents, had it continued to them, and ſo from one Generation to another. But in caſe any of <hi>Abraham's</hi> immediate Children, as in the Caſe of <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> or of ſuch Parents as had taken hold of the Covenant, as in the Caſe of <hi>Eſau,</hi> did apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize from God, they did thereby not only forfeit their own Intereſt in the Promiſe, but did cut off the Entail from their Poſterity: themſelves having loſt the Promiſe, or forfeited their Intereſt in it, their Children muſt needs loſe their Intereſt with them, and anſwerably they were to be caſt out of the Church, look'd upon and dealt with as <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the Covenant,</hi> and Promiſes of it, till them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhould perſonally repent and believe: and in ſome caſes were to be cut off by Death, and if they were not, it was the fault of thoſe in whoſe hands
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60484:14"/>the Adminiſtration of Church-Cenſures was put. But ſo long as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity did ſucceſſively, one Generation after another, embrace the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; ſo long the Promiſe was continued to them in the ſame extent and latitude in which it was at firſt given to <hi>Abraham.</hi> And as it was thus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the <hi>Jews,</hi> or natural Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo it is in reſpect of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Whoever under the firſt Teſtament was, or under the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to be accounted for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, they always had and have the Promiſe continued to them in the ſame extent, and yet with the ſame limitations, in and with which it was given to <hi>Abraham;</hi> though it is true, <hi>Abraham</hi> in ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects had a preheminence above any of his Seed, as in reſpect of Paternity or Father-hood, ſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Continuance of the Covenant amongſt his natural Poſterity; but this I ſay, Take <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> as a believing Parent of natural Children, ſo as the Promiſe was made at firſt to him, and his natural Children immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, ſo it always hath been and ſtill is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to all that were or are to be accounted for his Seed. And the Truth of this Propoſition is alike evident from Scripture with the Truth of the former. As,</p>
                  <div n="1" type="point">
                     <head>I. It is evident from the very Letter of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>I will be thy God, and the God of thy Seed, in their Generations.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>God, we ſee, promiſes not only to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, but to be a God to them in their <hi>Generations.</hi> Now in this Phraſe, [<hi>their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>] their Children are included. [<hi>Thy Seed in their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60484:14"/>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi>] in this latter Branch of the Promiſe, is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to [<hi>thee and thy Seed</hi>] in the former Branch of it, as that was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> as a natural Father of natural Children; for God to promiſe to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed <hi>in their Generations,</hi> is all one as if he had, (as before he did to <hi>Abraham</hi>) promiſed to be a God to them and their natural Children: So that in this Phraſe, <hi>in their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> is included the natural Children of all thoſe to whom the Promiſe doth appertain.</p>
                     <p>For the clearing up of this it muſt be premiſed, That in the ſame Sence this Branch of the Promiſe is to be interpreted, as it had reſpect and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the Jews, who were <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity; in the ſame Sence it is to be interpreted as it had reſpect, has been, or is continued to thoſe who from among the Gentiles were or are to be accounted the Seed intended in this Promiſe. And the Reaſon is evident, becauſe the Jews, his natural Seed, as grown up to years of maturity, held their Intereſt in the Promiſe, not meerly as his natural, but as his Spiritual Seed, as is partly evident from what is already ſaid, and will more abundantly appear from what follows. Hence undeniably, as, this Phraſe in this Promiſe was to be interpreted, as it reſpected the natural Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo it is to be underſtood as reſpecting the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now that this was the Sence of this Promiſe, as it reſpected <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed and Poſterity, is evident three ways.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe it can be no otherwiſe underſtood, but the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God will be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached thereby. Let any other Sence imaginable be put upon this Branch of the Promiſe, and it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60484:15"/>will be found inconſiſtent with the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God in his Promiſes: for there is no other Sence, beſides that afore menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, can with any ſhew of reaſon be put upon it, except only this, <hi>viz.</hi> That when God promiſed to be a God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his <hi>Seed in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> his meaning was, That he would be a God to them in the ſeveral Ages and Generations of the World, wherein they ſhould reſpectively live. But now this Sence is utterly inconſiſtent with the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God, in as much as in caſe this had been the ſence and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Branch of the Promiſe, then each one of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity would have had par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Intereſt in it, and conſequently God had engaged Himſelf to be a God to each of them: for in caſe this Phraſe [<hi>thy Seed in their Generations</hi>] ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends not the Promiſe beyond thoſe immediatly and firſtly intended in that Term [<hi>Seed</hi>], then the Promiſe, to whomſoever it ſhould appertain, would have been a particular Promiſe, entitling each of them to the God promiſed. That it is to be underſtood as a particular Promiſe, as appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Children, immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, and to his Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Seed, entitling each of them to the Good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, is paſt all rational doubt, and will be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proved hereafter: and anſwerably, in caſe that Phraſe, <hi>in their Generations,</hi> ſhould not extend the Promiſe beyond thoſe firſtly and immediatly intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Term (<hi>Seed</hi>), it muſt be ſo underſtood as appertaining to all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity; for that it did and doth in ſome ſence appertain to them, is expreſly declared in Scripture. But now
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60484:15"/>it is undeniable, that God was not the God of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed <hi>in their Generations</hi> in this Sence; there were many of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in after generations that God was not a God unto: So that let Men ſtudy to the utmoſt, they will never be able to find out any other Sence of this Promiſe, than that I have before given, as it reſpected <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity, but it will be found inconſiſtent with the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God in his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Secondly,</hi> That this is the true ſence and meaning of this Branch of the Promiſe, is evident, becauſe God himſelf ſo expounds it, when he comes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to deal with the <hi>Jews</hi> in a Covenant-way; thus <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.10, 11, 12, 13. There we ſhall find, when God comes to renew his Covenant with him, he takes in their <hi>natural Children</hi> with themſelves, as Parents, into Covenant with Himſelf, and that in proſecution of this very Promiſe. In the <hi>11th verſ.</hi> it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>The Covenant was entred with their little Ones.</hi> And that this was in proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this Promiſe is expreſly affirmed, <hi>v.</hi> 13. And that he did not take them in meerly as they were of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, is in part evident, and will further appear in the next particular. So that God himſelf expounds this Phraſe, <hi>in their Generations,</hi> as including Parents and Children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That this is the ſence and meaning of this Branch of that Promiſe, is evident <hi>de facto. Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity ſo long as the Covenant was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued among them, yea, not only his natural Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but alſo ſuch who from among the Gentiles took hold of the Covenant, enjoyed the Promiſe as including their Children with them. Parents
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60484:16"/>and Children were always Joint-Heirs of the ſame Promiſe; what Parents ſoever, whether <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> had the Promiſe appertaining to them, their Children had it alike appertaining to them. Now this is evident paſt all rational doubt theſe three ways.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, From the conſtant application of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Covenant, and that according to the appointment of God himſelf, to their Children, that both the <hi>Jews,</hi> and thoſe who from among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> joined themſelves to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, were according to the appointment of God to, and anſwerably did, apply the Token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant to their Children, is ſufficiently evident throughout the Old-Teſtament, and is denied by none.</p>
                     <p n="2">2dly. This is evident from the Ground upon which the Token was applied to them, and that was their Intereſt in the Promiſe. And that the Token of the Covenant was applied upon that Ground, is ſufficiently evident from what hath been already ſaid. For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It was applied under that very Notion and Conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> as the <hi>Token of the Covenant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. The Application and Reception of it is ſaid to be the keeping of the Covenant.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. The Command enjoining of it was grounded upon Intereſt in the Covenant.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Otherwiſe God could not truly ſay, it was the Token of the Covenant between him and thoſe to whom it was applied, which yet he doth.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Becauſe otherwiſe it had been the univerſal Duty of all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, deſcended as well by <hi>Iſhmael</hi> as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and by <hi>Eſau</hi> as <hi>Jacob,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60484:16"/>the uſe of Circumciſion throughout all Ages, though rejected of God from being his People, which is abſurd to imagine.</p>
                     <p n="3">3dly. Let this be added, that the Promiſe could not appertain to the Children we now ſpeak of, neither could they have been in Covenant, unleſs included in this Phraſe, <hi>Thy Seed in their Generations.</hi> That they had an Intereſt in that Promiſe, and were in Covenant, is undeniable from what hath been already ſaid. Now I ſay, they could have had no Intereſt in that Promiſe, neither could have been in Covenant, had they not been included in that Phraſe: For,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. It cannot be ſuppoſed, neither will any af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, they could have that Promiſe appertaining to them by virtue of any perſonal Act of their own: by what way, or through what means then can they be ſuppoſed to have had ſuch an Intereſt in the Promiſe, but only this, that it did reach and take in Children with their Parents? If any ſhall ſay, it was by virtue of their Relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as his Seed, though mediatly deſcending from him. To that I anſwer. That there is no Ground for this pretence, in reſpect of the Children of thoſe who from among the Gentiles embraced <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Covenant, they were not either immediatly or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly deſcended from <hi>Abraham;</hi> hence in reſpect of the Children of Proſelytes, there is no other way imaginable how they ſhould come to an Intereſt in the Promiſe, and without that they could not have had the Token of the Covenant applied to them, which undeniably they had, but that before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>viz.</hi> through the extent of the Promiſe as made to Parents and Children, in this Phraſe, <hi>Thy
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60484:17"/>Seed in their Generations.</hi> And as for the Children of thoſe who were of the natural Poſterity of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> neither could they have the Promiſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to them, as deſcended from him, and that is undeniable from hence, becauſe their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, as grown up to years of maturity, and as Parents they muſt be granted ſo to be, they had not the Promiſe continued to themſelves meerly as of the natural Poſterity of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but as having perſonally taken hold of the Covenant themſelves, and ſo as Believers, and conſequently as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Myſtical Seed. The truth is, that none of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s natural Seed, whether grown up to years of Maturity, or Infants, beyond thoſe immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, as <hi>Iſhmael, Iſaac,</hi> &amp;c. and they too only during their Infant-ſtate, had an actual and perſonal Intereſt in, or Right to the Covenant, or Promiſes of it, meerly as his Seed, or as of his natural Race and Poſterity. This is evident: for,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. If any had an Intereſt in the Promiſe meerly as of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity, then all his Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> would have had a like intereſt In it: but it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly certain that all had not.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. In caſe <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity had had an Intereſt in the Covenant and Promiſes, meerly as ſuch, beyond his immediate Children; then Breach of Covenant on their part had been ſimply and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impoſſible, and conſequently they muſt neceſſarily have continued in Covenant till the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant it ſelf had been repealed, (which to this day is not, as will appear more fully by and by) and have enjoyed the full Good promiſed.</p>
                     <p>But now to ſay that Breach of Covenant on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60484:17"/>their part was impoſſible, is not only to contradict plain Scripture, but to charge God with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Unfaithfulneſs and Injuſtice. How came ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity to be caſt out of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, if Breach of Covenant had been impoſſible on their part? Or if they are not caſt out of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, how comes it to paſs that they enjoy not the Benefits of it? But that the Covenant is broken on their parts, is undeniable; which had it apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to them meerly as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity, had been impoſſible, for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Poſterity they ſtill are.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. In caſe all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Race and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity had the Covenant with the Promiſes of it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to them, meerly as his Seed; and if any as ſuch had, then all had, as is proved before; then none of them could have been juſtly or righteouſly finally cut off, caſt out, or excluded from, either the Covenant, or Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> either by the hand of God, or by any Eccleſiaſtical Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. But that ſome, yea, or any of them, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their Apoſtacy from God, might be juſtly and righteouſly cut off, caſt out, and exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and that finally, from the Covenant, and Common-wealth of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> either the one or the other way, is certain. So that none of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Poſterity, beyond his immediate Children, had an actual perſonal Intereſt in the Covenant, or had the Promiſes appertaining to them, meerly as or becauſe they were of his Poſterity. And hence it will undeniably follow, that all thoſe of his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, that being grown up to years of Maturity, had their Intereſt in the Covenant continued to them, it was not meerly becauſe they were of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60484:18"/>Poſterity, but becauſe themſelves had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally taken hold of the Covenant, and ſo were become his Myſtical as well as his Natural Seed; and all their Children had their Intereſt in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, not from their Relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as of his natural Poſterity, but from their Relation to their immediate Parents, by virtue of this Promiſe made to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed <hi>in their Generations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now then let but what hath been ſaid be well weighed, and fully underſtood, and no rational Scruple can remain in the Minds of any about the Truth of what we affirm. That which we affirm, is this, That the Covenant, and in particular this Promiſe of God's being a God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his natural Seed immediatly proceeding from his own Loins, was continued to his Seed, whether they were <hi>Jews,</hi> or Proſelyted Gentiles under the firſt Teſtament, in the ſame latitude and extent in which it was eſtabliſhed with, and made to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> at the firſt.</p>
                     <p>We ſee it is evident, Firſt, from the very <hi>Letter of the Promiſe.</hi> And that that is the true meaning of that Promiſe is evident, becauſe no other Sence can be put upon it; but the Truth and Faithfulneſs of God is impeached thereby, God himſelf ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, and the <hi>Jews</hi> ſo enjoyed it throughout all Ages.</p>
                     <p>And in the ſame extent and latitude in which the Covenant and Promiſes were continued to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed under the firſt Teſtament, in the ſame extent and Latitude they are continued to his Seed under the ſecond Teſtament, which evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, not only from hence, namely, Becauſe the Promiſe equally and alike concerns New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Believers,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60484:18"/>as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed under the firſt Teſtament, and no Alteration appears to have been made in the tenour of the Covenant, in regard of its latitude and extent. Which alone might ſuffice, ſeeing it muſt needs be high Preſumption for any to make any Alteration in the Covenant beyond what God hath done. But I ſay it appears not only from hence, but alſo from the Conſideration of the Notion under which thoſe that then had the Promiſe appertaining to them and their Children were look'd upon, <hi>viz.</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Myſtical or Spiritual Seed, which is the very ſame Notion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which Believers ſtill are look'd upon, as having the Promiſe appertaining unto them.</p>
                     <p>Now when the People of God under the firſt Teſtament had the Promiſe continued to them in this extent and latitude, <hi>viz.</hi> as reaching to and taking in their Children with them, and this as they were conſidered under this very Notion, as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Myſtical or Spiritual Seed. Who can entertain the leaſt doubt, whether it be continued in the ſame extent and latitude to the People of God under the ſecond Teſtament, ſeeing both thoſe under the firſt Teſtament, and theſe under the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Teſtament are alike included in, and ſpoken to in one and the ſame Promiſe, and that as look'd upon in the Promiſe under the ſelf-ſame Notion and Conſideration?</p>
                     <p>Theſe things carry ſo much Evidence, that were they well conſidered, it may ſeem even impoſſible, but that this Controverſy, among all Perſons that give themſelves up to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Scriptures, muſt needs have a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod put unto it; and indeed it may ſeem utterly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60484:19"/>ſuperfluous to add any thing more, and therefore I ſhall more contract in what remains.</p>
                     <p>But to proceed, the Truth of this ſecond Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is evident.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="point">
                     <head>II. From the <hi>Promiſes and Prophecies of the Old-Teſtament, referring to New-Teſtament times.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>They evidently ſhew, that God intended this Promiſe ſhould be continued to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, that is, <hi>Believers under the New-Teſtament,</hi> in the ſame extent and latitude in which it was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> at firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> as taking in Parents and their Children. Thus it is evidently propheſied of, and promiſed to ſome, as in particular the <hi>Jews,</hi> that under the New-Teſtament they ſhould enjoy this Promiſe in the ſame extent and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in which it was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that is, That God would be a God to them and their Children with them. The Prophecies and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are obvious to all, that will but conſult theſe Scriptures; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.3. &amp; 59.21. &amp; 65.23. <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.21, 22. Who, that reads theſe Scriptures, eſpecially as expounded by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.26. by that univerſal Phraſe, <hi>All Iſrael ſhall be ſaved,</hi> can doubt whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Jews</hi> at their future Call and Converſion ſhall enjoy this Promiſe in the extent and lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude before mentioned? Surely all Men muſt unavoidably grant that they ſhall, neither do I know that any have expreſly denied it. Now it is certain they ſhall be received into the ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that Believers are now under, they ſhall not
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60484:19"/>have another Covenant diſtinct from that at preſent made with Believers. This is evident by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8. Now the Covenant being one and the ſame, all the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of it may and ought to be indifferently applied unto all under it, and conſequently to believing Gentiles, as well as to the <hi>Jews</hi> at that their Call and Converſion; I mean, they may and ought to be applied indifferently both to believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and to the Jews, when the Good contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them is not, either by the nature or kind of it, nor by any revelation from God, reſtrained to the Jews, as the Good of this Promiſe is not. And that we may and ought to apply ſuch Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, though firſtly and directly made to the <hi>Jews,</hi> to believing Gentiles, is ſufficiently evident from the Apoſtles application of Promiſes to belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which were firſtly and immediatly made to the <hi>Jews.</hi> Compare <hi>Jerem.</hi> 31.31. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10. <hi>Amos</hi> 9.12. with <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16. Theſe Promiſes primarily and principally reſpect the <hi>Jews</hi> at their future Converſion; yet, we ſee, the Apoſtle applies them to the Goſpel-Chuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this preſent Adminiſtration. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner are thoſe other Promiſes, concerning God's <hi>pouring out his Spirit and Bleſſing upon the Off-ſpring of his People,</hi> his <hi>being a God of all the Families of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. And the like may and ought to be applied to believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> though they have a moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect reſpect to the <hi>Jews.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>So that it is evident from theſe Prophecies and Promiſes, that God intended to continue, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably has continued this Promiſe in the ſame
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60484:20"/>extent in which it was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles. The Promiſe is ſtill to them and their Seed, that is, their natural Children, as it was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his natural Children.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond ſubordinate Propoſition further confirmed, and that both from the expreſs Words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Gal. 3.14.</hi> And from ſeveral New-Teſtament-Scriptures, as laid together, and compared one with another. Three Concluſions drawn from them. Two Inferences drawn from thoſe Concluſions. Three Objections anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="2 (cont.)" type="proposition">
                  <p>THat this Promiſe is ſetled upon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to believing Gentiles, in that extent and latitude mentioned, is evident,</p>
                  <div n="3" type="point">
                     <head>III. From the <hi>expreſs Letter of the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Thus in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13, 14. the Apoſtle tells us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, That Chriſt <hi>hath redeemed us from the Curſe of the Law, himſelf being made a Curſe for us, that the Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>might come upon the</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles <hi>through him.</hi> So that it is according to the expreſs Letter of this Scripture, that the <hi>Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>is come upon the believing</hi> Gentiles
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60484:20"/>
                        <hi>through Chriſt.</hi> Hence the only Queſtion is, what this Bleſſing is? Now this the Apoſtle ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declares in the <hi>9th</hi> verſe of this Chap. where he tells us, that they that <hi>are of the Faith,</hi> that is, true Believers, <hi>they are bleſſed with faithful</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, that is, they are bleſſed with the ſame Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that he was bleſſed with: Now this was the Bleſſing he was bleſſed with, <hi>viz.</hi> that God was his God, and the God of his Seed; that is, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore proved, his natural Seed. It is true, there were other Bleſſings conferred upon <hi>Abraham;</hi> but that the Bleſſing contained in that grand Promiſe of the Covenant is this very Bleſſing the Apoſtle hath reſpect unto, and doth intend, is undeniable, for theſe three Reaſons.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe the Apoſtle expreſſeth himſelf in an indifferent or univerſal Term, <hi>the Bleſſing,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Bleſſing contained in this Promiſe, cannot be excluded, whatever other Bleſſings are included.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Becauſe all other Bleſſings conferred upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> were ſuch, as each believing Gentiles is unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of enjoying, as to be <hi>the Father of the Faithful,</hi> to have the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> deſcend from their Loins. Theſe and the like Bleſſings are not compatible to every particular Believer; ſo that no other Bleſſing that <hi>Abraham</hi> was bleſſed with, can be intended.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Eſpecially becauſe the Apoſtle muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily have reſpect to this very Promiſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Bleſſing contained in it muſt needs be the Bleſſing ſaid by him to be come upon the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> through Chriſt. This is evident from the <hi>16th</hi> verſe of this Chap. where the Apoſtle cites this very Promiſe, to prove what he had affirmed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60484:21"/>this <hi>14th</hi> verſe, concerning the Bleſſing of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> its being come upon the <hi>Gentiles</hi> through Chriſt. Now unleſs he had intended the Bleſſing intended in that Promiſe, his Citation of it to prove what he affirms in this <hi>14th</hi> verſe, had been impertinent. And beſides, the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>verſe</hi> 29. <hi>That if we be Chriſt's, then we are Heirs according to the Promiſe.</hi> He doth not, it's true, expreſs what we are Heirs unto, but this <hi>14th</hi> verſe tells us, it is the Bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> that is the <hi>Good</hi> we are Heirs of; <hi>Now,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we are Heirs of this Bleſſing according to the Promiſe.</hi> According to what Promiſe? Why that Promiſe mentioned <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. For that is the Promiſe that evidently the Apoſtle intends. Hence this [<hi>Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>come upon the Gentiles</hi>] muſt neceſſarily be that very Bleſſing contained in that Promiſe, and that was, That as God would be <hi>a God</hi> to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, that is, primarily his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Seed, ſo he would be a <hi>God to his Seed in their Generations,</hi> that is, to them and their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Children, which is the ſame Bleſſing that <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> himſelf was bleſſed with.</p>
                     <p>So that we ſee by the expreſs words of the Apoſtle, the Promiſe is granted unto, and ſetled upon believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the ſame extent and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude in which it was made to <hi>Abraham.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="point">
                     <head>IV. and laſtly, That this Promiſe is continued to all his Seed, and in particular to believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, in the ſame latitude and extent in which it was made to <hi>Abraham,</hi> may be infallibly conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from <hi>ſeveral Paſſages in the New-Teſtament,</hi> as laid together and compared one with another.</head>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:60484:21"/>
                     <p>The Paſſages amongſt others are theſe, <hi>Mark</hi> 10.10. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.9. <hi>acts</hi> 2.38, 39. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. From theſe Paſſages, as laid toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and compared one with another, we may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer theſe three Concluſions, from all which the Truth aſſerted will evidently appear.</p>
                     <p n="1">I. That upon any Parents believing in Chriſt, the Promiſe of Salvation belongs not only to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but to their reſpective Houſes; not only themſelves as perſonally conſidered, but their Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes come under the Promiſe of Salvation. This is evident from <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.9. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. compared together. Our Lord Chriſt tells <hi>Zaccheus, Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> upon his believing, <hi>was come unto his Houſes</hi> that is, as the Apoſtle explains it, his Houſe was now under the Promiſe of Salvation. What Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation he means is evident from the Apoſtles words, namely, <hi>Eternal Salvation,</hi> as begun in this Life; therefore ſaith he, <hi>Thou and thy Houſe ſhall be ſaved,</hi> which is all one as to ſay, Salvation ſhall come to thy Houſe; for Salvation to come to a Houſe, is all one as to ſay, that Houſe ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or is under the Promiſe of Salvation. Hence no Man can rationally interpret <hi>Salvation,</hi> in that Paſſage of Chriſt to <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> of Chriſt himſelf. Indeed Chriſt is no where in Scripture called Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ſimply and abſolutely, nor can Chriſt poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly intend himſelf, becauſe he lays the Ground of this <hi>Salvation</hi>'s coming to <hi>Zaccheus</hi>'s Houſe, in that new Relation he was received into unto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> he was now become his Son, and upon that very Ground Chriſt tells him, <hi>Salvation was come to his Houſe.</hi> Now that cannot be ſuppoſed to be the Ground upon which Chriſt himſelf came to his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:60484:22"/>Houſe; he came rather that he might become a Son of <hi>Abraham,</hi> than becauſe he was ſo; ſo that he muſt needs here intend <hi>Salvation</hi> in a proper ſence. So that we ſee expreſly, that upon Parents believing, the Promiſe of <hi>Salvation</hi> belongs to their Houſes.</p>
                     <p n="2">II. That under this Term [<hi>Houſe</hi>] the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of believing Parents are in a peculiar and an eſpecial manner included and intended. I do not deny, but the Term [<hi>Houſe</hi>] may take in more than their Children; but that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, cannot be rationally queſtioned. Hence for Salvation to come to the Houſes of believing Parents, is all one as to ſay, <hi>Salvation</hi> is come to their Children. For as our Lord Chriſt tells <hi>Zac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheus, Salvation</hi> was come to his Houſe; ſo the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> aſſizes the Jaylor, that upon his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving his <hi>Houſe ſhould be ſaved;</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> tells the Jews, that upon their believing, the Promiſe would be to them and their Children; and our Lord Chriſt tells us, that <hi>of ſuch</hi> (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Children) <hi>is the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Now all theſe Paſſages, as in the general, and for the ſubſtance, intend one and the ſame thing, ſo they mutually explain and confirm each other.</p>
                     <p>Hence for any to underſtand [<hi>Salvation</hi>] of Chriſt himſelf, or [<hi>Houſe</hi>] of <hi>Zaccheus</hi> himſelf, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unreaſonable, (<hi>Salvation,</hi> when abſolutely put, never ſignifying Chriſt, nor a Man's ſelf ſaid to be his <hi>Houſe</hi>) but it is to ſhut their Eyes againſt that Light the Holy Ghoſt himſelf holds forth for the diſcovery of the Mind and Meaning of our Lord Chriſt in that Paſſage to <hi>Zaccheus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:60484:22"/>
                     <p n="3">III. That Salvation belongs to the Houſes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to the Children of believing Parents, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as ſuch, that is, as they are the Children of ſuch Parents, without conſideration had to their perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Faith and Repentance. Now this, which it is true is moſt liable to exception, may be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niably demonſtrated, not only from the Letter of the forementioned Paſſages, no mention being made of the Faith and Repentance of thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>Salvation was come to them,</hi> or the Promiſe is to them, but from a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Conſideration.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Promiſe of Salvation belongs to the Houſes, that is, as before, the Children of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving parents, meerly by virtue or on the account of ſuch a Relation they ſtand in to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as is common to all Believers, this is that of Children. Thus ſaith Chriſt, <hi>This day is Salvation come to thy Houſe, foraſmuch as he alſo is the Son of</hi> Abraham. Mark what it is that our Lord Chriſt grounds his Aſſertion upon, it is evidently <hi>Zaccheus</hi> his Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>Abraham, as his Seed.</hi> And the like muſt be underſtood as the Ground of that Promiſe of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Jailor; he and his Houſe upon belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving would come under the Promiſe of Salvation, foraſmuch as he then would become a <hi>Son of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> as God promiſed to <hi>Abraham, to be a God to him and his Seed,</hi> which is all one as to ſay, <hi>to him and his Houſe;</hi> ſo that he would <hi>be a God to his Seed in their Generations,</hi> which is all one as to ſay, <hi>to them, and their Houſes.</hi> So now <hi>Zaccheus,</hi> being through his Faith in Chriſt become one of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed, our Lord Chriſt tells him, <hi>Salvation was come to his Houſe;</hi> he, and his Houſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:60484:23"/>his Children, were now under the Promiſe of Salvation, which is the ſame for ſubſtance with that of God's <hi>being a God to them.</hi> Neither can any with any ſhew of Reaſon plead the neceſſity of Faith, or the actual Calling or Converſion of <hi>his Houſe,</hi> to their Joint-Intereſt with him in this Promiſe; ſeeing not only there is no ſuch Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation intimated to be neceſſary; but on the other hand, their Intereſt is evidently declared by our Lord Chriſt to be <hi>Zacheus</hi>'s Relation to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> as one of his Seed; our Lord Chriſt ſpeaks of the Time preſent, <hi>Salvation</hi> was then <hi>come to his Houſe,</hi> upon the very firſt Moment of his believing, and that upon this very account that he now was become a <hi>Son of Abraham.</hi> And this Good, <hi>viz.</hi> to have <hi>Salvation come to his Houſe,</hi> being vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to him upon that Ground, it muſt needs be a Good common to all ſtanding in the ſame Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him to <hi>Abraham.</hi> To ſay to a Man, when made free of a City or Town Corporate, this or that is now your Priviledge, as ſuppoſe to uſe any Trade, or the like, foraſmuch as you know your ſelf are made free, it evidently ſhews that ſuch a Priviledge is common to all that are free of ſuch a City. or Town Corporate. So now when our Lord Chriſt ſaith to <hi>Zaccheus, Salvation was come to his Houſe,</hi> upon that Ground, becauſe he was a <hi>Son of Abraham,</hi> it undeniably implies, that it is a Priviledge common to all believing Parents, as they are the Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and conſequently Salvation muſt needs appertain to the Houſes of all Believers, as ſuch, without Conſideration had to any Qualification of thoſe intended in this Term [<hi>Seed</hi>].</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:60484:23"/>
                     <p n="2">2. That the Promiſe of Salvation belongs to the Houſes of believing Parents, upon their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal believing, is evident from hence; becauſe the Miniſters of the Goſpel may be warrant from God apply the Promiſe of Salvation to their Houſes, upon the ſole account of their own perſonal belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. This is evident from the Promiſe of <hi>Paul</hi> to the Jaylor, he promiſed him, that upon his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving both he and <hi>his Houſe ſhould be ſaved.</hi> Now look as the Apoſtle doth propoſe this Promiſe to the Jaylor, as a Motive to him to believe, it might have been applied to him upon his actual believing; upon the firſt moment of his believing, it might have been ſaid, Now the Promiſe of Salvation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to <hi>thee</hi> and <hi>thy Houſe;</hi> or <hi>thou and thy Houſe ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Now what the Apoſtle did or might have done, every Miniſter of the Goſpel may do in the like caſe upon Parents believing; they may apply the Promiſe of Salvation not only to them as perſonally conſidered, but to them and their Houſes. And if it ſhould be ſaid, that as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Salvation was propoſed only conditionally to the Jaylor himſelf, ſo it muſt be underſtood as referring unto his Houſe, as the Apoſtle aſſures him, that if he ſhould believe he ſhould be ſaved, ſo he only aſſures him, that if his Houſe ſhould believe, they alſo ſhould be ſaved. But now for this, there can be no rational Pretence for ſuch a ſence of the Apoſtle's words, not only becauſe they are expreſt and poſitive without any intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any ſuch Condition in reſpect of his Houſe; but more eſpecially, becauſe in caſe the Apoſtle had not intended a peculiar Good accruing to his Houſe upon his own perſonal believing, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:60484:24"/>could be nothing elſe but their Intereſt in, and Right to the Promiſe of Salvation. There can be no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon imagined why he ſhould add the latter Branch of the Promiſe, concerning his Houſe, ſeeing whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he had believed or no, his Houſe ſhould have been ſaved upon condition of their believing; nor to propoſe that as a Motive to induce him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, which he might have been aſſured of though he had not believed, had been impertinent, yea, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd. It muſt be ſomething accruing to his Houſe by his believing, that muſt rationally be an Induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him to believe. To tell him, that upon his believing, and that as a Motive to him to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, his Houſe ſhould be ſaved, when they were brought into no other Capacity in reference to Salvation than they were before, or would have been, ſuppoſing he ſhould not have believed, had been ridiculous. Hence, unleſs we will charge the Apoſtle with as great an Abſurdity as well Man could be guilty of, we muſt grant he intended as he ſpeaks, <hi>viz.</hi> That upon the Jailors believing, both <hi>himſelf and Houſe ſhould be ſaved,</hi> that is, they ſhould come actually under the Promiſe of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which in caſe they ſhould not forfeit by their after failing in performing their Duties indiſpenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly required to their actual enjoying that Salvation which at preſent they were actually under the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of, they ſhould infallibly enjoy it. For that muſt ſtill be remembred, that though upon Parents perſonal Faith, their Houſes, and eſpecially their Children, come under the Promiſe of Salvation; yet their future Enjoyment of it neceſſarily ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes their own performance of the Condition of the Covenant of Grace, as they grow up to years
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:60484:24"/>of maturity; and ſuppoſing there ſhould be any Children in ſuch Houſes, as are actually grown up, when their Parents do believe, though a Right to, and Intereſt in the Promiſe accrues to them as the Children of ſuch Parents; yet unleſs they conſent to, and take hold of the Covenant, they do <hi>ipſo facto</hi> forfeit their Right to and Intereſt in it: But this we ſee evidently, that upon Parents belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, their Children have a Right to and an Intereſt in the Promiſe of Salvation, without conſideration had to any Qualifications in them: which ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently ſhews that the Promiſe, which was the thing to be proved, is continued to believing Gentiles, in the ſame extent and latitude in which it was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> at the firſt eſtabliſhment of the Covenant with him. The Promiſe was to him and his natural Children; ſo it is to Believers, and their natural Children, or (which is all one) to them <hi>n their Generations.</hi> From what hath been ſaid, two things may be inferred.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That it is all one as to the proof of Childrens Intereſt in the Promiſe, whether <hi>Zaccheus</hi> or the Jaylor had any Infants at that time. If they had any, the Promiſe did belong to them; if they had none, yet the Promiſe did belong to their Houſes. And the ſame is true of the Houſes of all Believers; if they have any Infants, the Promiſe belongs to them; if they have none, yet the Promiſe apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains unto ſuch as are included in the Term [<hi>Houſe</hi>].</p>
                     <p n="2">2. We may infer, That the Scriptures ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times mentioning the Faith and Repentance of the Houſes, or of ſome in or of the Houſes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving parents, do no way oppoſe, but on the other
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:60484:25"/>had ſtrongly confirm the Truth of this ſecond Propoſition. Their being ſavingly wrought upon together with or immediatly after their Parents Converſion, hinders not but that the Promiſe might belong to them, as the Houſes, or as of the Houſes of believing Parents; but on the other hand, rather proves that it did. Becauſe we read of the Faith and Repentance of ſome in or of the Houſes of Believers, ſhall we hence conclude, that the Promiſe did not belong unto them as the Houſes of ſuch Parents? how unreaſonable would that be! We may rather conclude the Promiſe did belong unto them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="objections_answered">
                  <p>But to haſten: By what hath beeen ſaid, our two firſt Propoſitions are abundantly, yea, ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abundantly eſtabliſhed; and the Truth is, the Truth of theſe two firſt Propoſitions appears with ſo much evidence throughout the whole Scriptures, that it is even a wonder how any of a competent underſtanding, that are able to compare one Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with another, can queſtion the one or the other: yea, I dare boldly ſay, there is hardly any one Truth in the whole Doctrine of Divinity hath a more full Suffrage from the Scriptures, than this concerning the Covenant-Intereſt of the Seed of Believers hath. How many plain and expreſs Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures have we for it? And the Evidence given in throughout the Scriptures to theſe two Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons being ſo plain and expreſs, it may ſeem whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuperfluous to take notice of any objections that may be made againſt them. To ſuppoſe that any thing may be juſtly objected from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures againſt the one or the other, is in effect to ſuppoſe that the Scriptures may contradict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:60484:25"/>And therefore I ſhall only take notice of three or four Objections, which our Oppoſers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive to have the greateſt weight in them.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Objection that I ſhall take notice of, is raiſed from that <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.7, 8. whereunto is added, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7. and <hi>Job.</hi> 8.33. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas the Apoſtle denies that the Children of the Fleſh are the Children of God; ſo he affirms, that the Children of the Promiſe are accounted for the Seed. So <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and our Lord Chriſt ſhew the Inſufficiency and Vanity of that Plea the Jews made for the continuance of their Covenant-ſtate, and Enjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all their Priviledges, Benefits, and Bleſſings, whether preſent or future, annexed thereunto, grounded upon their Relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as their Father.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 1.</head>
                     <p>Thus it is objected, <hi>That in caſe</hi> Abraham's <hi>own natural Seed could not have their Covenant-ſtate, with the Priviledges and Benefits thereunto annexed, continued to them under the Goſpel, upon the account of their Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to</hi> Abraham, <hi>as his Seed; much leſs can the Infants of any believing Gentiles be received into ſuch a State, and enjoy the Priviledges and Benefits of it upon the account pf their Deſcent from, and Relation to ſuch Parents.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>This Objection hath its riſe from the very ſame Miſtake about the true Mind and meaning of God in this grand Promiſe of the covenant, wherein he promiſeth to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in <hi>their Generations,</hi> which the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves lay under; the rectifying of which was the Deſign both of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> our Lord Chriſt, and the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:60484:26"/>Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> in the places mentioned. And the Miſtake is this, the Jews thought, and the Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers of this Objection will needs take it for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that this Promiſe did ſo appertain to all the natural Seed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whether immediate or mediate, as that they had univerſally a perſonal and particular Intereſt in it; and hence the <hi>Jews</hi> thought that they could not be caſt off, nor depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the Bleſſing and Benefits of the Covenant, without a failure on God's part in his Promiſe. Our Oppoſers ſeem to ſee no other way to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Faithfulneſs of God in their actual rejection, than by affirming this Covenant is diſanull'd, at leaſt the tenour thereof altered, ſo as not to take in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Seed, as it did (as they ſuppoſe) during the firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtration; but the Miſtake, as to the tenour of the Promiſe or Covenant, is the ſame in both. Now the rectifying of this Miſtake was the Deſign both of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> where let three things be conſidered:</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That neither <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> nor our Lord Chriſt, nor the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> do deny that the Promiſe had reſpect to them; yea, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth ſuppoſe, and implicitly grant that it had, which could be no other than that more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Reſpect before mentioned.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. That they all ſpeak to or of the <hi>Jews</hi> then in being.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. That they ſpeak to or of them, as grown up to years of maturity; and hence their Deſign is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew that the Promiſe, as made with ſuch a reſpect to them, did not infallibly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure their covenant-ſtate, nor their Enjoyment of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:60484:26"/>the ſaving Benefits and Bleſſings of the Covenant, without Faith, Repentance, and Holineſs on their parts; the Apoſtle withal ſhewing, that there was an Election of Grace, as he after ſpeaks, which did and ſhould obtain the Good promiſed, which they did in reſpect of thoſe who were grown up to years of maturity through their Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: but in reſpect of Infants, it was through the gracious Promiſe of God reaching and taking in them with their Parents; and hence neither the one or the other ſpeaks to or of the <hi>Jews</hi> in theſe places, carries the leaſt ſhew of Oppoſition to either of the foregoing Propoſitions; but on the other hand, as what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of them, taken in conjunction with the Context, undeniably implies the Truth of our firſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. So what they all ſpeak, adds no ſmall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation to the ſecond, as might eaſily be made appear, were it neceſſary. Let us only ſee the Truth of what we now affirm, <hi>viz.</hi> That which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is ſo far from carrying any Oppoſition to, that it evidently im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies the Truth of that Propoſition.</p>
                        <p>For the making of this plain it may be obſerved, that the Queſtion the Apoſtle is there reſolving, as is granted on all hands, and is evident from the Context, is, <hi>How ſo great a part of the Jews could be rejected and yet the Faithfulneſs of God in that Promiſe made of no effect thereby.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now for the Reſolution of this Queſtion, he firſt more generally aſſerts, that <hi>all the not</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that are of</hi> Iſrael. And then more particularly,
<list>
                              <item>1. Denies, <hi>That all the Seed of</hi> Abraham, that is, his natural Seed, <hi>were Children,</hi> that is, <hi>the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:60484:27"/>Children of God,</hi> as he expounds it, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. He denies not but that ſome were the <hi>Children of God;</hi> all that he denies is, that they were <hi>all</hi> ſo. And,</item>
                              <item>2. On the other hand affirms, <hi>That in</hi> Iſaac <hi>the Seed were to be, and anſwerably were called;</hi> which he explains in <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. namely, <hi>That the Children of the Promiſe were counted for the Seed.</hi> Where let it be obſerved, he ſpeaks not of that grand Promiſe of the Covenant, but of thoſe two Promiſes, the one made to <hi>Abraham</hi> concerning the Birth of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the other to <hi>Rebecca,</hi> concerning the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of <hi>Jacob</hi> above <hi>Eſau;</hi> and by the <hi>Children of the Promiſe</hi> he means the Elect.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>Now theſe are ſuch he accounted for the Seed, that is, they are the Perſons deſigned to enjoy the Good promiſed. For the illuſtration and confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which, he ſhews, That Perſons might be Subjects of this Promiſe of the Covenant, yet not be Children of God, nor <hi>accounted for the Seed,</hi> that is, not appertain to the Election of Grace, and conſequently might not enjoy the Good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed; and yet this no Impeachment of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of God in the Promiſe. And then ſhews it was ſo,
<list>
                              <item>1. Among <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children, deſcended from his own loins.</item>
                              <item>2. It was ſo among <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Children, who were Subjects of this Promiſe, as included with <hi>Iſaac</hi> their Father, in that Phraſe, [<hi>thy Seed in their Generations</hi>] <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, 9, 10. Hence he argues <hi>a fortiori,</hi> If it might be thus in reſpect of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s own Children, and in reſpect of his next Son's Children, who had the Promiſe appertaining to them as ſeverally and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly conſidered; much more it might be ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:60484:27"/>reſpect of thoſe, who were the Subjects of this Promiſe only, as it had a more general reſpect to them, as of <hi>Abraham's</hi> Poſterity. But hence it is evident, the Apoſtle is ſo far from denying, either that <hi>Abraham</hi>'s own Children, or <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Children, were Subjects of this grand Promiſe of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, that he plainly grants and ſuppoſes that they were: for in caſe the Apoſtle did not ſuppoſe and take it for granted, that the reſt of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children had been accounted the Subjects of this Promiſe with <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Iſaac</hi>'s Children with <hi>Jacob,</hi> his inſtancing in them, as being the <hi>Children of God, and accounted for the Seed,</hi> had made nothing to his purpoſe, conſidering the Queſtion he was now reſolving, but would rather have made againſt the Reſolution he gives of that Queſtion, as will evidently appear to any that ſhall throughly weigh the whole Context. So that this Text of the Apoſtle is ſo far from oppoſing, that it doth greatly eſtabliſh the Truth of our firſt Propoſition; the Apoſtle evidently granting that <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children by <hi>Keturah,</hi> were the Subjects of this Promiſe as well as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> as well as <hi>Jacob.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 2</head>
                     <p>It is ſaid by ſome, <hi>That this Covenant, the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of which with</hi> Abraham <hi>and his Seed in their Generations is recorded,</hi> Gen. 17.7. <hi>is not that Covenant of Grace under which Believers under the New-Teſtament are. Hence though this Covenant eſtabliſh'd with</hi> Abraham <hi>did run in that latitude and extent pleaded for,</hi> viz. as taking in Parents with their natural Seed under the Firſt-Teſtament; <hi>yet no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument can be drawn from thence to prove that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:60484:28"/>of Believers are ſtill taken into covenant with their Parents, ſeeing the Covenant under which Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers now are, is a Covenant quite different from this eſtabliſhed with</hi> Abraham, <hi>this being the Old, and that the New Covenant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>This Objection will be ſufficiently removed by the Proof of theſe two Propoſitions,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That this Covenant then eſtabliſhed with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> was a Covenant of Grace, that is, a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant aſſuring of Spiritual Bleſſings, the very ſame Bleſſings aſſured and conveyed to Believers by the Covenant they are now under; and a Covenant aſſuring of ſuch Bleſſings will doubtleſs be granted by all Men to be a Covenant of Grace. That this was ſuch a Covenant will appear by theſe four Conſiderations.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That in caſe this Covenant only aſſured <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>his Seed in their Generations,</hi> of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Good; then many thouſands that were the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Subjects of it, and that as perſonally and particularly conſidered, might and did never enjoy and Good or Benefit by it; and this without any default on the part either of themſelves, or any others through whoſe default they could be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be juſtly deprived thereof, and conſequently meerly through God's not performing his Promiſe. This is evident thus, Becauſe many thouſands, that were the undoubted Subjects of this Covenant, might and did die in their pure Infant-ſtate, and conſequently were utterly uncapable of enjoying any temporal Good. Hence in caſe this Covenant only aſſured of a temporal Good, all thoſe ſo dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing muſt needs fall ſhort of the Good promiſed.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:60484:28"/>And this could not be through any default of their own, ſeeing they were (as in their Infant-ſtate) uncapable of doing either Good or Evil. And this might be, and often was found true in reſpect of the Seed of Believers, and conſequently no for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of the Promiſe was made by their Parents; hence their not enjoying the Good of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſuppoſing it to be only temporal, could be aſſigned to no other Cauſe, but meerly God's not performing his Promiſe. But now it is certain, none ever did or ſhall fall ſhort of any Good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, meerly through a Failure on God's part in making good his Promiſe. Hence it muſt needs be a Spiritual Good, which might be enjoyed in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Life, that was the chief and principal Good intended in this Promiſe.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Conſider the Subject Matter of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or the Good promiſed, and that was, that <hi>God would be a God to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and his Seed in their Generations.</hi> Now the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> expreſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers this above any temporal Good whatſoever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. laſt verſe. And conſequently it muſt needs be a Spiritual Good, ſeeing it is impoſſible that there ſhould be any Good that is greater than any temporal Good, and yet it ſelf is no ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Good.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Conſider, that the Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which according to the Letter of the Promiſe only intended a temporal Good, yet ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to a more inward and Spiritual Sence did intend a Spiritual Good, <hi>viz.</hi> Heaven, as is evident from <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.9, 10. and is acknowledged (at leaſt) by ſome of our chief Oppoſers. And how unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and abſurd is it to imagine, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:60484:29"/>which according to the Letter intends only a temporal Good, ſhould yet according to a more inward and Spiritual ſence intend a Spiritual Good; and yet that this Promiſe of <hi>God's being a God to them,</hi> which according to the very Letter intends a Spiritual Good, ſhould only intend a temporal Good.</p>
                        <p n="4">4. Conſider that this Promiſe, as is granted on all hands, intends a Spiritual Good, as made to <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual or Myſtical Seed, and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably muſt needs intend the like Good as made to his natural Seed; ſeeing God hath no where in his Word given us a Warrant to interpret it of one kind of Good as made to his Myſtical Seed, and of another kind of Good as made to his Natural Seed. So that this Covenant muſt neceſſarily be a Covenant of Grace, the Good contained in it was a ſpiritual and Eternal Good; and ſuch a Good can be granted to, or enjoyed by Man as now fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, by no Covenant but what is a Covenant of Grace. But,</p>
                        <p n="2">II. That this covenant mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was the very ſame for the Subſtance of it, that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers under the New-Teſtament are under. It is not only a Covenant of Grace, but the very Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace that Believers are ſtill under. Now this is undeniably evident from the Apoſtle's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe in <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. Let only two things be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. The Apoſtle poſitively affirms that this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant was never diſanull'd or abrogated. Thus verſ. 17. <hi>This I ſay, That the Covenant which was before confirmed of God in Chriſt, the Law, which was four hundred and thirty years after, cannot diſanull,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:60484:29"/>that it ſhould make the Promiſe of none effect.</hi> That the Apoſtle ſpeaks of this very Covenant made and eſtabliſh'd with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is ſufficiently evident from the whole Context. 'Tis that Covenant, the grand Promiſe whereof ran in that tenour, <hi>To thee, and to thy Seed;</hi> ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 16. Which muſt needs be this Covenant, no other Covenant made with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> containing any Promiſe to his Seed, running in that tenour. Now ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>The Law, which was four hundred and thirty years after, could not diſanul this Covenant;</hi> ſo that this Covenant was not diſanull'd by the Law. And let it be carefully obſerved, that in caſe it had been diſanull'd at any time before our Lord Chriſt came in the Fleſh, yea, or by him when he was come, (and that it hath been diſanull'd at any time ſince, or by any other, I ſuppoſe no Man will affirm) it had been all one as to the Apoſtles deſign; for if it had been diſanull'd before Chriſt came, or by him when he was come, the Apoſtle could not have proved, that the <hi>Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>was come upon the Gentiles through Chriſt,</hi> as believed in, (as we ſee he doth from the tenour of that Covenant) any more than if it had been <hi>diſanull'd by the Law.</hi> So that undoubtedly, this Covenant is the very Covenant under which Believers ſtill are.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Let is be conſidered, that it is by virtue of this very Promiſe contained in this Covenant that Believers are <hi>Heirs of the Bleſſing of Abraham,</hi> thus <hi>verſ.</hi> 29. So that not only <hi>the Bleſſing of</hi> Abraham <hi>is come upon believing Gentiles,</hi> but is come upon them through this very Promiſe, and that as they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered under the Notion of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, which puts the matter out of doubt. When Believers are
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:60484:30"/>under this very Promiſe, or Heirs to the Good or Bleſſing contained in it, as they are <hi>Abraham's</hi> Seed, who can doubt whether the Covenant, the grand Promiſe of which they are under, and that as they are become <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, be that Covenant that they are now under? So that that Covenant eſtabliſh'd with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is the very ſame Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace that Believers are now under, is too evident to be denied by any that are but indued with human Modeſty.</p>
                        <p>And whereas ſome may yet ſay, The Scripture ſeems evidently to diſtinguiſh between that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant the Jews were under during the Old-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-Adminiſtration, and that Believers are under ſince the Goſpel-Adminiſtration, calling the one the <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> the other the <hi>New.</hi> The Anſwer is at hand, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is readily granted, that the <hi>Jews</hi> were under a Covenant that Believers now are not under; but that was not that Covenant made with <hi>Abraham,</hi> but the Covenant made at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> Hence the Covenant, the New-Teſtament calls the <hi>Old Covenant,</hi> was that made at Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and not this made with <hi>Abraham.</hi> The words are plain, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. latter end. <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.8.</p>
                        <p>So that it is paſt all rational doubt, it was the Covenant of Grace, that very Covenant that Believers are now under, that was eſtabliſh'd with <hi>Abraham,</hi> the Eſtabliſhment of which is recorded <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. And here we might further confirm what hath been hitherto pleaded for, namely, that the grand Promiſe of the Covenant is continued to Believers under the New-Teſtament in the ſame extent and latitude, <hi>viz.</hi> as including their Infant-Seed with them, in which it was at firſt made
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:60484:30"/>to <hi>Abraham;</hi> for if the Covenant be the ſame, the Promiſes of it muſt needs be continued in the ſame tenour in which they were at firſt made, unleſs God himſelf and made any alteration, which it is certain in this reſpect he hath not done. Theſe things appear with ſo much evidence, that it is to admiration how they ſhould meet with any Contradiction from any that pretend to take the Scripture as the Rule of their Faith and Practice.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="objection">
                     <head>Object. 3.</head>
                     <p>It may be ſome will yet further ſay, <hi>That ſuppoſe it be granted, that the Covenant then eſtabliſh'd with</hi> Abraham <hi>was not only a Covenant of Grace, but the Covenant of Grace under which Believers always have been, and ſtill are; ye the Infant-Seed of the People of God under the Firſt-Teſtament might be only under the external Adminiſtration of it, and not taken in as Parties in the Covenant it ſelf; and hereupon that Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration ceaſing, they are no ways concerned in the Covenant, either in regard of the Adminiſtration, or the Subſtance of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <head>Anſwer.</head>
                        <p>'Tis true, ſome ſeem to think ſo, but their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes are cloathed with ſuch Confuſion and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, that it is hard to find out what they mean. But that Infants were not only under the external Adminiſtration of the Covenant, but were taken in as Joint-Parties with their Parents in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant it ſelf, is ſuperabundantly evident from what hath been already ſaid. Thoſe that were under the moſt eſſential Promiſe of the Covenant, muſt ſurely be under or in the Covenant it ſelf. Now I have ſufficiently proved, that Infants of Govenant-Parents were from the firſt eſtabliſhment
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:60484:31"/>of the Covenant under the Promiſe of <hi>God's being a God to them,</hi> which is the moſt eſſential Promiſe of the Covenant, yea, a Promiſe that virtually comprehends the whole Good contained in the Covenant. So that undoubtedly they were not only under the external Adminiſtration, but in the Covenant it ſelf.</p>
                        <p>Poſſibly ſome will yet ſay, Grant them to have been under this Promiſe, and anſwerably in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, yet might not this Promiſe, at leaſt as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to Infants, be an Appendix to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and not of the Eſſence or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it, as the Promiſe of the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan</hi> was.</p>
                        <p>To that I anſwer; No, 'tis a Promiſe that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly appertains to the Eſſence of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; 'tis that which (as I have ſaid) virtually includes the whole Good of the Covenant. And how abſurd and unreaſonable would it be to take the Promiſe as made to Parents as of the Eſſence of the Covenant, when yet as made to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, as only an Appendix to it, eſpecially when it is but one Promiſe, conſiſting of two Branches, made to one and the ſame Perſon? Neither doth the Scripture give the leaſt Ground for ſuch an Imagination.</p>
                        <p>Now theſe Objections being anſwered, I ſhall proceed to the third Propoſition; only as previous thereto, let it be obſerved, That I have been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto only proving the Intereſt of the Infant-Seed of Believers in the Covenant, and in ſpecial in that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:60484:31"/>grand Promiſe of it, concerning <hi>God's being a God to them.</hi> And this was abſolutely neceſſary to be proved before their Right to Baptiſm be proved, ſeeing their Right to Baptiſm follows upon cheir Intereſt in the Covenant, and is applied to them on that Ground.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The third ſubordinate Propoſition laid down, proved three ways; further confirm'd from thoſe Inſtances of whole Houſes being bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, recorded in Scripture.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="3" type="proposition">
                  <head>Prop. III.</head>
                  <p>THe third Propoſition then is this,
<q>That all thoſe that are under, or are the actual Subjects of that grand Promiſe of the Covenant, wherein God promiſeth <hi>to be a God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and his Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations,</hi> are the due Subjects of Baptiſm, and ought according to the revealed Will of our Lord Chriſt to be baptized.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the Infant-Seed of Believers are the proper Subjects of that Promiſe, hath been already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. I am now to prove, that they being under, or the proper Subjects of the Promiſe, are the due Subjects of Baptiſm. Now this may be eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced paſt all rational Contradiction theſe three ways.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:60484:32"/>
                  <div n="1" type="proof">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>From the Command of God, enjoining and expreſly requiring all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations to keep the Covenant. The words are expreſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9. <hi>And God ſaid to</hi> Abraham, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore, thou, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And that it may clearly appear, how this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand doth warrant, yea, require the Application of Baptiſm to the Infant-Seed of Believers as they are Subjects of the Promiſe, theſe five things muſt be diſtinctly proved.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That by <hi>[Covenant]</hi> in this Command, is meant the <hi>[Token of the Covenant].</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That the Covenant of Grace always had, and ſtill hath an out outward Token annexed to it.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That this Command obligeth, not only Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to have the Token applied to themſelves, but to apply it, or to take care that it be applied to their Infant-Seed, as Joint-Subjects with them of the Promiſe.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That as Circumciſion was the Token of the Covenant during the Old-Teſtament-Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo Baptiſm is the Token of the Covenant under the New.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That this Command doth equally and alike concern Believers with reſpect to Baptiſm, as it did the <hi>Jews</hi> with reſpect to Circumciſion.</p>
                     <p>Theſe five things being cleared up, and proved, what we affirm will be ſufficiently eſtabliſhed. And therefore for the firſt.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That by the <hi>Covenant</hi> in this Command is meant the <hi>Token of the Covenant.</hi> This is plain from the Verſe immediatly following. Only let it be obſerved, that the Covenant is firſt more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:60484:32"/>laid down, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant, thou, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations.</hi> And then what ſhould be this Covenant at that time, during the firſt Adminiſtration, is declared in the next Verſe, it ſhould be <hi>Circumciſion.</hi> The Command requires the keeping of the <hi>Covenant</hi> in general. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is ſpecified to be the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> at that time to be kept, though not the only Covenant to be kept.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That this Covenant, which hath been alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy proved to be the Covenant of Grace, always had, and was to have, and conſequently ſtill hath a Token annexed to it. This is evident,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. From the expreſs Letter of the Command. We evidently ſee the Command is given to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s <hi>Seed in their Generations,</hi> that is, to all his Seed in their Generations. 'Tis not limited to either his Natural or Spiritual Seed, but takes in both. And that this Command reacheth <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual Seed, as well as his Natural, is further evident, becauſe the ſame Perſons muſt needs be intended in the Command, that are intended in the Promiſe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. Now <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Spiritual, as well as his Natural Seed, were undoubtedly intended in the Promiſe. Hence this Command obligeth the one as well as the other. So that while <hi>Abraham</hi> had a Seed upon the Earth, <hi>they in their Generations,</hi> that is, they and their Children, are under the Obligation of this Command, which undoubtedly proves that this Covenant always had, and was to have a Token annexed to it, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe God would not command <hi>Abraham's Seed in their Generations to keep the Covenant,</hi> unleſs there had been a Covenant, that is, a Token to be kept.</p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:60484:33"/>
                     <p n="2">2. And yet further, this is evident <hi>de Facto,</hi> that there always has been, and ſtill is a Token an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Covenant. That it had a Token an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it during the Old-Teſtament-Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, is granted by all; and that it ſtill hath a Token, and that Baptiſm is that Token, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear when I come to the fourth Particular. And therefore,</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That this Command obligeth Parents, not only to have the Token applied to themſelves, but to apply, or take care that it be applied to their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed. This is evident two ways.</p>
                     <p>(1.) From the expreſs Letter of the Command, <hi>Abraham's Seed in their Generations</hi> are expreſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to keep the Covenant, and under that Phraſe <hi>[their Generations]</hi> we are to include their Infants; both Parents and Children are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded in the Promiſe, and conſequently both muſt needs be included in the Command. So that Children are under the Command to <hi>keep the Covenant,</hi> which in reſpect of them can only intend their reception and bearing of the Token of it, and ſo they are under the Obligation to keep it. Whence they, not having it applied to them, are ſaid to break the Covenant. And if they are thus far to keep it, it will undeniably follow that it is their Parents duty to take care that it be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to them.</p>
                     <p>(2.) This is evident from the Diſpleaſure of God againſt Parents, when the Application of the Token of the Covenant to their Children hath been neglected, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.24, 25, 26. From whence it is plain, that as the Infants of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, be they <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> are under the Obligation
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:60484:33"/>to <hi>keep the Covenant,</hi> that is, the Token of it; ſo it is the Duty of Parents to take care that it be applied to them, and anſwerably that they do keep it.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That as Circumciſion was the Token of the Covenant under the Firſt-Teſtament, ſo Baptiſm is the Token of the Covenant under the New. That Circumciſion was the Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant under the firſt Teſtament is expreſly declared, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.19. And that Baptiſm is the Token of the Covenant under the New-Teſtament, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the general.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe unleſs Baptiſm be the preſent To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, the Covenant hath no Token at all, which we proved before it was to have. Now if Baptiſm be not the Token, what is the Token to be kept? The Command is yet in force, therefore there is a Token ſtill to be kept. But now there is no To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken can with any ſhew of Reaſon be ſuppoſed to be intended in this Command, but only Baptiſm, and therefore that muſt needs be the preſent To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Covenant.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. This will more fully appear, if we compare Baptiſm with Circumciſion, the former Token of the Covenant. Look what Ordinance under the New-Teſtament moſt exactly agrees with Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and ſerves to thoſe uſes and ends, for or with reference unto which a Token was annexed to the Covenant, that muſt needs be the preſent Token, and that is undeniably Baptiſm. For let us but conſider what were the Uſes and Ends with reference whereunto Circumciſion the firſt Token of the Covenant was appointed, and we ſhall find that Baptiſm is appointed with reference to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:60484:34"/>the very ſame Ends and Purpoſes. As for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</p>
                     <p>(1.) Circumciſion, as the Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, was that ſolemn Rite or Ordinance whereby Perſons were admitted into, and incorporated in the Church viſible. Now that Baptiſm is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, and ſerves to the ſame uſe and end, is plain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</p>
                     <p>(2.) Circumciſion was appointed for the ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, confirming, and aſſuring to thoſe that were the Subjects of the Covenant all that Good, or all thoſe Benefits and Bleſſings contained in it. Hence it is ſaid to be to <hi>Abraham,</hi> a <hi>Seal of the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Faith.</hi> And of what uſe it was unto him with reſpect unto the Righteouſneſs of Faith, of the ſame uſe it was to him with reſpect to the whole Good of the Covenant. And look of what uſe it was to <hi>Abraham,</hi> of the ſame uſe it was to all that were the due and proper Subjects of it, ſeeing he received it not only as a particular Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, but as the Father of, and anſwerably was in his receiving of it the Pattern to all that ſhould be received into the ſame Covenant with himſelf; and of the ſame uſe is Baptiſm, as is evident, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. with <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38.</p>
                     <p>(3.) The uſe and end of Circumciſion was to engage thoſe to whom it was applied to keep ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly to the Articles of the Covenant. Hence they are ſaid to be <hi>circumciſed to the Lord,</hi> Jer. 4.4. And for the ſame end again Baptiſm is appointed; hence the Baptized are ſaid to be <hi>baptized into or unto the Name of the Father, the Son, and Holy-Ghoſt, and into or unto Chriſt, Mat.</hi> 28.19. with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.</p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:60484:34"/>
                     <p>(4.) Circumciſion was appointed a viſible Badge whereby the People of God were diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the World. And of the ſame uſe is Baptiſm, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. afore cited. Now from the Uſes and Ends that the Scriptures declare Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion was appointed for, and did ſerve unto, we may ſee what were the Uſes and Ends in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, for or with reference unto which a Token was annexed to the Covenant. And from the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſm with Circumciſion, in reſpect of the Ends and Uſes the one or the other were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for, it evidently appears that Baptiſm is the preſent Token of the Covenant, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably is that Ordinance appointed and ſubſtituted in the room and ſtead of Circumciſion.</p>
                     <p>And as a Cloſe to this, let it be obſerved, that though it ſhould be granted that there were ſome Uſes and Ends, for and with reference unto which Circumciſion was inſtituted, in reſpect of which Baptiſm agrees not with it; yet that hinders not, but that Baptiſm may be and is the preſent Token of the Covenant, ſeeing it ſerves to, and performs all thoſe Uſes and Ends that a Token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant under the New-Teſtament can be ſuppoſed to ſerve to and perform. But,</p>
                     <p n="5">5. That this Command doth equally and alike concern Believers and their Seed, as it did concern the People of God and their Seed under the firſt Teſtament. As it obliged them to be circumciſed themſelves, and to take care that their Infant-Seed were circumciſed with them; ſo it ſtill obligeth Believers to be baptized themſelves, and to take care that their Infant-Seed be baptized with them. And this is evident from the Conſideration of two things in the Command.</p>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:60484:35"/>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Command, as firſtly and more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally laid down, did not determine what the Token of the Covenant ſhould be, and hence was applicable, and did oblige to whatever Token God ſhould inſtitute. The words are plain and expreſs, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant, thou, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations;</hi> nor thou ſhalt be circumciſed or be baptized, but thou <hi>ſhalt keep my Covenant,</hi> that is as afore, the Token of the Covenant. Hence as this Command, as thus generally laid down, no more obliged to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, than to Baptiſm; all that it obliged to was to <hi>keep the Covenant.</hi> So when Circumciſion was inſtituted, it obliged to that; but when Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion was laid aſide, and another Token inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which is Baptiſm, it now obligeth to that, ſeeing the Command in the general is not revoked, only the Token altered; but the Command is ſtill the ſame, and obligeth to keep the Covenant ſtill, and anſwerably it obligeth Parents to have the Token applied to themſelves, and take care that it be applied to their Children.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider the Extenſiveneſs of the Command. It is laid upon <hi>Abraham</hi>'s <hi>Seed in their Generations,</hi> without any limitation, and hence reacheth to, and lies upon <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed under the New-Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as well as it did upon his Natural Seed under the firſt Teſtament. So that the Command not determining what the Token ſhould be, only enjoining the keeping of it, whatever it ſhould be, and conſequently being applicable to Baptiſm as well as to Circumciſion, and extending to and reaching all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and conſequently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles as well as the Jews; it is all one
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:60484:35"/>as if God had ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant, thou, and thy Seed after thee, their Generations.</hi> Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under the Firſt-Teſtament, and Baptiſm under the ſecond, theſe being the Covenants ſucceſſively the one after the other to be kept. So that here is an expreſs Command for the Baptiſm of Infants, though not in the very Term <hi>[Baptiſm],</hi> yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this general Notion, as it is the Token of the Covenant.</p>
                     <p>That Baptiſm is the preſent Token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, is before proved. That this Command requires all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and that in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, including both Parents and Children, to keep the Covenant, that is, the Token of it, is according to the expreſs Letter of the Command.</p>
                     <p>And that believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> as <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed, and that under that Phraſe, <hi>[thy Seed in their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations]</hi> are included both Parents and Children, hath been abundantly proved. So that ſtill to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire a Command for Infant-Baptiſm, is little leſs than to reject the Scriptures. What though it be not commanded under that preciſe Term of <hi>[Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm]</hi> ſeeing it is commanded under that Notion, as the Token of the Covenant? And what though Infants are not expreſly mentioned, ſo long as they are undeniably included in the Command, in that Phraſe, <hi>[thy Seed in their Generations]?</hi> Surely it is all one as if they had been expreſly mentioned.</p>
                     <p>Now that this is the true ſence of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, might be further ſhewn from the Lords va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Phraſe when he inſtitutes Circumciſion, the then Token of the Covenant, and from the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of interpreting other Commands, as the prohibiting the making of graven Images, ſo the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:60484:36"/>requiring the Obſervation of the Sabbath after the ſame manner. But that's for the firſt way how this laſt Propoſition may be proved, and ſo I ſay it may be proved from the Command lying upon all that are the Subjects of this Promiſe, <hi>to keep the Token of the Covenant,</hi> that is, to receive and bear it, which Token to be kept is at preſent Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="proof">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>That the Infant-Seed of Believers, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or as the Subjects of the Promiſe, may and ought to be, and anſwerably in Primitive Times; and that from the very firſt Inſtitution of Baptiſm, were baptized, may be proved thus, <hi>viz.</hi> Becauſe they as the Subjects of the Promiſe do appertain, and were owned and looked upon, both by our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as appertaining to his viſible Church, Kingdom and Body. Now all that do appertain, and anſwerably were owned and look'd upon by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to his viſible Church, Kingdom and Body, may and ought to be, and anſwerably were baptized, cannot be rationally queſtioned, becauſe Baptiſm was inſtituted for this very end, ſolemnly to admit and incorporate into the viſible Church, Kingdom; or Body of Chriſt all that do apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thereunto, and there was no other way or means appointed for that end and purpoſe. Hence all that do appertain, or were owned and look'd upon, either by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, as apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to his viſible Church, Kingdom, or Body, may and ought to be, and anſwerably were ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and incorporated thereinto this way, <hi>viz.</hi> by Baptiſm.</p>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:60484:36"/>
                     <p>That Baptiſm was appointed for this end and purpoſe, is plainly expreſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13. And that there is any other way appointed for that end and purpoſe, is not, neither can be affirmed by any. Now that Infants, as under, or as the Subjects of the Promiſe, do appertain to the viſible Church, Kingdom, or Body of Chriſt, and were owned and look'd upon ſo to do both by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is plain.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Becauſe as under the Promiſe, and in Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with God, they are, as perſonally and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly conſidered, the actual Subjects of the Promiſe of Salvation. Now whoſoever is, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally and particularly conſidered, an actual Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the Promiſe, they muſt needs appertain to the viſible Church, Kingdom, or Body of Chriſt. Chriſt is only the <hi>Saviour of his Body,</hi> Eph. 5.23. Though it is true, Chriſt in a large ſence may be, and is in Scripture ſaid to be the Saviour of all Men, and the <hi>Saviour of the World;</hi> yet none but ſuch as are Members of his Myſtical Body, at leaſt do appertain thereunto, and have a right of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion thereinto, are under the Promiſe of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by him, as perſonally and particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. Hence all others are ſaid to be <hi>Strangers to the Covenants of Promiſe,</hi> Eph. 2.12. So that the Infant-Seed of Believers being under the Promiſe of Salvation by Chriſt, and that as perſonally and particularly conſidered; and he being only the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of his Body, they muſt needs appertain to his Body, and anſwerably ought to be admitted and incorporated into it, which can be no other way but by Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That the Infant-Seed of Believers do apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:60484:37"/>to the viſible Church, Kingdom, or Body of Chriſt, and were owned and looked upon ſo to do by our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, becauſe the Apoſtle expreſly tells us, that the <hi>Promiſe was made unto Chriſt,</hi> meaning it of Chriſt Myſtical, that is, the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, And that the Apoſtle here ſpeaks of the Myſtical Body of Chriſt as viſible, is ſufficiently evident, becauſe particular and individual Perſons might be ordinarily known to appertain to the Body of Chriſt, as here ſpoken of. Hence ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. ſpeaking to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> as viſible Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, <hi>Ye are all one in Chriſt.</hi> Now it cannot be ſuppoſed, that every individual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon among the <hi>Galatians</hi> were really of the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Body of Chriſt. The Apoſtle ſufficiently implieth his Fears of the contrary, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.4. ſo again, <hi>chap.</hi> 4. <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, &amp; 20. But yet not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo far apoſtatized as to diſanull their Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in the Body of Chriſt, he tells them they <hi>were all one in Chriſt,</hi> which undeniably ſhews the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks of the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. Now we evidently ſee he owns all to whom the Promiſe appertains, to appertain to the viſible Body of Chriſt; or as the Promiſe conſtitutes of the Body, ſo it appertains to them as Members of it. Now I ſay, they appertaining to, and being owned by Chriſt and his Apoſtles ſo to do, to the viſible Church, Kingdom, and Body of Chriſt, they undoubtedly may, and ought to be, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerably were by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, or by others by their allowance and direction admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and incorporated thereinto by Baptiſm.</p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:60484:37"/>
                     <p n="3">3. That Infants as under this Promiſe may an ought to be, and anſwerably were in Primitive Times baptized, is yet further evident, becauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> plainly declares, that Intereſt in this Promiſe is alone by it ſelf a ſufficient Ground for the application of Baptiſm. Hence he exhorts thoſe awakened Jews to be baptized upon this Ground, or for this Reaſon, <hi>that the Promiſe did belong unto them,</hi> Acts 2.39. ſaith he, <hi>Be baptized for the remiſſion of Sin, for the Promiſe is to you.</hi> It is true, he exhorts them to Repentance, with which Faith muſt be conjoin'd as neceſſary to their Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Promiſe; but it was their Intereſt in the Promiſe, that he grounds his Exhortation to them to be baptized upon. Hence however Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons come to have an Intereſt in the Promiſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by their deſcent from Covenant-Parents, or by their own perſonal Faith and Repentance, it is all one as to our preſent purpoſe. 'Tis their Intereſt in the Promiſe that is the proper Ground, and that alone is a ſufficient Ground for the appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Baptiſm, <hi>Be baptized, for the Promiſe is to you;</hi> not, be baptized becauſe you have repented, but becauſe <hi>the Promiſe is to you.</hi> And this is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the firſt Command to keep the Covenant, that is, the Token of the Covenant; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is grounded upon Intereſt in the Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Thou ſhalt keep my Covenant therefore,</hi> that is, upon this Ground, becauſe the Promiſe is unto thee, and having the Promiſe, thou ſhalt upon thy Intereſt therein keep my Covenant. So that Intereſt in the Promiſe is a ſufficient Ground for the application of Baptiſm, and Infants having an Intereſt in the Promiſe they have a ſufficient
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:60484:38"/>Ground for the application of Baptiſm to them, and anſwerably may and ought to be baptized. And that which may yet further aſſure us, that it is Intereſt in the Promiſe that is the alone Ground, and that that is a ſufficient Ground for the applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Baptiſm, is the Reference that Baptiſm hath to the Promiſe. It hath no neceſſary refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Repentance, nor Repentance any neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reference unto it; and hence Baptiſm may be applied where Repentance goes not before, as is evident in the caſe of <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> and our Lord Chriſt himſelf. 'Tis the Promiſe alone that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm hath a neceſſary reference unto. Hence who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever have an Intereſt in the Promiſe, they are the true and proper Subjects of Baptiſm, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably ought, (as in Primitive Times they had to have it applied to them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="proof">
                     <head>IV.</head>
                     <p>For the further Confirmation of this laſt Propoſition, namely, That the Seed of Believers, as being under the Promiſes of the Covenant, may and ought to be baptized; let the ſeveral Inſtances of Houſholds being baptized be duly weighed. That whole Houſholds, together with the Heads or Governours of them reſpectively, were frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly baptized, is expreſly declared in Scripture, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15, 33. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.16. Now that we may ſee what Evidence theſe Inſtances give to the Truth pleaded for, let three things be conſidered.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That there is a very great Probability, if not an abſolute Certainty, that if not all, yet ſome in or of theſe Houſholds were baptized, as the Seed of believing Parents, without reſpect had to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Qualifications of their own. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:60484:38"/>(if not Certainty) of this will appear, if we firſt conſider that we muſt comprehend all the natural Seed in thoſe Houſholds ſaid to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, Whoever were comprehended, yet none of the Children ought to be excluded. We muſt take the words of the Holy Ghoſt according to their proper ſence and ſignification. Now the words do neceſſarily include their Children.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Theſe Houſe or Houſholds may be rational<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſed to be conſiderably great. Theſe Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Houſholds, all his,</hi> and the like, are a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ground for ſuch a Suppoſition.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That not only Infants new born, but Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, as arrived to a higher ſtate of Childhood or Youth muſt be ſuppoſed to be baptized upon the account of their Fathers Faith, ſuppoſing there were any ſuch in thoſe Houſholds. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this is evident, becauſe it cannot with any ſhew of reaſon be ſuppoſed, that ſuch Children, though arrived to ſome uſe of Reaſon, could yet attain to ſuch a meaſure of Knowledg in the Myſteries of the Goſpel, as would have been ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to qualify them for Baptiſm, had they been to be baptized on their own account, in ſo ſhort a time as did intervene between the Converſion of Parents, and the Application of Baptiſm. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, though paſt meer Infancy, yet while in their Youth or Childhood, cannot be ſuppoſed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Knowledg of Goſpel-Myſteries in the ſame ſpace of time that Perſons come up to their full maturity may do. So that it muſt be either granted, that ſome in or of theſe Houſholds were baptized as the Children of believing Parents, on the account of their Parents Faith; or we muſt
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:60484:39"/>either deny, not only that there were any pure In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, but any Children in their Childhood or Youth in theſe Houſes; or elſe we muſt contradict the expreſs Letter of the Scriptures. But now to deny the former, is at leaſt (to ſay no more) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what unuſual; that ſo many Houſes, and theſe conſiderably great, ſhould not only have no meer Infants, but no Children yet in their Childhood or Youth, is utterly improbable; and to depart from the Letter of the Scriptures, where there is no reaſon why we ſhould ſo do, is not only unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but in a ſence impious. So that theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances made it at leaſt exceeding probable, that ſome were baptized as the Children of believing Parents, without conſideration had to any perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Qualifications of their own. Houſholds were baptized, and it can hardly be ſuppoſed that ſo many Families, and theſe conſiderably great, ſhould have neither any new born Babes, nor yet any as yet in their Childhood or Youth; and if any ſuch there were, they muſt be baptized upon the account of their Parents Faith.</p>
                     <p>This will more clearly appear, if we take a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular account of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Houſe, ſaid to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with her, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15. For, 1. It is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent her Houſhold was with her at that Aſſembly to whom the Apoſtle preached, as appears from ver. 15. 2dly, It's evident that this was an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Women, verſ. 13. 3dly, There's no mention made of the converſion of any, excepting. <hi>Lydia</hi> her ſelf. Now that <hi>Lydia</hi> ſhould have an Houſhold all of Women, as ſo they muſt be in caſe ſhe had no Children, and theſe grown up and all converted at one and the ſame Sermon, when not
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:60484:39"/>one in the whole Aſſembly beſides was converted, and yet that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould take no notice of any of their Converſions, but only of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s her ſelf, ſeems utterly improbable. That ſuch a thing is poſſible cannot be denied, but ſure that it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable muſt be granted. As for thoſe Brethren mentioned verſ. 40. there is no rational ground to ſuppoſe that they were of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Houſhold ſaid to be baptized. It is certain they were not, for they were all at the Aſſembly with her, which is expreſly ſaid to have been an Aſſembly of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. But,</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Let it be conſidered that it doth not appear from Scripture, that my one in or of thoſe Houſholds ſaid to be baptized, were converted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Baptiſm, excepting only the Perſons whoſe Houſholds they were. This is evident paſt all Contradiction in reſpect of <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Houſhold. And as for the Jailor's, though it be ſaid, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas ſpake to him to Words of the Lord, and to all that were in his Houſe;</hi> yet,</p>
                     <p>(1.) From this it cannot be concluded, that any ſaid to be baptized were converted before their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.33. ſeems to intimate that it was after; and beſides, all things are not recorded in the Scriptures exactly in the order in which they were done.</p>
                     <p>(2.) It doth not appear, that thoſe to whom the Word was ſpoken were the ſame individual Perſons ſaid to be his, who were baptized, they ſeem rather to be the Priſoners, and thoſe that appertained to the Priſon, as Under-keepers, and ſuch like.</p>
                     <p>(3.) Though ſome of them might be the ſame
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:60484:40"/>Perſons, yet it doth not appear that they were converted by the Word. So that from theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages it cannot be proved, that any of his, ſaid to be baptized with him, were converted before their Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p>And as for what is ſaid concerning his rejoicing, <hi>be with his Houſhold believing in God;</hi> if the words were rightly tranſlated, they are ſo far from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Converſion of his Houſhold before their Baptiſm, that they rather intimate the contrary; they ſhould be tranſlated, <hi>He rejoiced with his Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, he believing in God.</hi> And the Apoſtle laying the Ground of his Houſholds rejoicing in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Faith, ſeems plainly to imply, that the Good that was the matter of their Joy, did ariſe from his Faith.</p>
                     <p>And as for <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Houſhold, there is nothing evidencing that any of them were converted before their Baptiſm, although it is ſaid, they addicted themſelves to the Miniſtry of the Saints, yet that they were the ſame Perſons intended in that Term <hi>[Houſhold]</hi> ſaid to be baptized, is uncertain; or ſuppoſe ſome of them might be, yet whether they were converted before their Baptiſm is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; how long this Epiſtle was written after he and his Houſhold were baptized, we cannot ſay; ſome then in their Childhood might be grown up to a capability of miniſtring to the Saints when this Epiſtle was written.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Let it be conſidered in the laſt place, that though it ſhould be granted, that ſome in or of thoſe Houſholds might be converted before their Baptiſm, yet from thence it cannot be concluded, that all intended in theſe Terms [<hi>Houſes</hi> or <hi>Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds</hi>]
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:60484:40"/>were ſo. Suppoſe ſome in the Jailor's Houſe might be concerted before their Baptiſm, yet it will not follow from thence, that all were ſo: and much leſs will it follow, that there were none in <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Houſe baptized, but ſuch as did perſonally believe. Now if there be but a proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, that any one in or of theſe Houſholds ſaid to be baptized, were baptized on the account of their perſonal Faith, that gives as full an evidence to the Truth pleaded for, as the probability of all in thoſe Houſes being baptized on the ſame account would do. So that ſure it cannot be denied, but that all theſe Inſtances do at leaſt make it probable, that ſome were baptized in Primitive Times, as the Children of believing Parents, without Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration had to any thing in themſelves; and a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability added to thoſe foregoing Arguments may greatly eſtabliſh us in the Truth pleaded for. But as a Cloſe of all, let theſe two things be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. The utter Improbability, in caſe it had been the will of our Lord Chriſt that none but adult Believers ſhould be baptized, that the Holy Ghoſt ſhould leave upon record the Baptiſm of ſo many Houſholds, and yet leave it utterly uncertain whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any in or of theſe Houſholds were baptized on the account of their perſonal Faith and Repentance, eſpecially there being ſo great a Probability, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the account he gives us of ſome of thoſe Houſholds, that there muſt needs be ſome more of them, who muſt be baptized on the account of their Parents Faith. We cannot reaſonably ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that the Holy Ghoſt would record theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſo as to give ſo great an occaſion of Miſtake
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:60484:41"/>to the People of God, to take up a Practice ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to the Honour of Chriſt, and his Intereſt in the World, as our Oppoſers ſuppoſe the Baptiſm of Infants to be, in caſe it had been the will of our Lord Chriſt they ſhould not be baptized.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider how the Holy Ghoſt doth vary his manner of expreſſion, when he ſpeaks of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Houſholds, and when he ſpeaks of the Baptiſm of others. When he ſpeaks of the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Houſholds, he tells us of their Baptiſm to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the chief Heads and Governors, not taking the leaſt notice of the Faith of any in or of thoſe Houſholds, as the Ground of their Baptiſm; but when he ſpeaks of the Baptiſm of others, he ſpeaks more diſtinguiſhingly, <hi>So many as gladly received the Word, were baptized.</hi> And why the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt ſhould not expreſs himſelf after the ſame manner, when he ſpeaks of the Baptiſm of Houſholds, no rational account can be given, ſave only this, that it is to ſhew, that as the Covenant with the Promiſe thereof is continued to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Seed of Believers; ſo that the preſent Token, which is Baptiſm, ſhould be applied unto them.</p>
                     <p>But to have done with this: From all that hath been ſaid, our three foregoing Propoſitions are ſufficiently evident, and from all our main Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>viz. That it is the Will of our Lord Chriſt, that the Infant-Seed of his People ſhould be baptized, fully eſtabliſhed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:60484:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Sundry Objections anſwered. The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="objection">
                  <head>Object. 1.</head>
                  <p>THE main and chief Objection againſt Infant-Baptiſm, and that which alone is of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable weight, is that raiſed from <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. compared with <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16. where we have the Inſtitution of Baptiſm, as ſome (though groundleſly) would have it rather the Commiſſion, authorizing and enjoining the Adminiſtration of the Ordinance among the Gentiles recorded. And I find our Oppoſers grounding their Plea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Infant-Baptiſm upon this Commiſſion, two ways.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>Some argue from a threefold Suppoſition, which they conceive this Commiſſion lays a fair Ground for, as differently recorded by thoſe two Evangeliſts.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That that Relative Term <hi>[them]</hi> muſt refer to <hi>[Diſciples],</hi> ſuppoſed to be included in the word which we tranſlate, <hi>teach,</hi> or as others would have it, <hi>diſciple</hi> or <hi>make Diſciples,</hi> as its Antecedent, and not to that word <hi>[Nations].</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2. That Infants not being capable of teaching, neither are, nor can in propriety of Speech be ſaid to be <hi>Diſciples.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:60484:42"/>
                     <p n="3">3. That this Inſtitution or Commiſſion is to be underſtood as excluding all from Baptiſm, who are not comprehended in it; hence they argue, that the Subjects propoſed by our Lord Chriſt to be baptized being Diſciples, and Infants not being, nor in propriety of Speech can be called Diſciples; and all others beſides Diſciples being excluded by Chriſt, his propoſing them only to be baptized; hence Infants neither may nor ought to be baptized.</p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <p>In Anſwer to this we ſay, That all theſe Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions are utterly groundleſs and falſe.</p>
                        <p>For the firſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>[them]</hi> muſt refer to Diſciples included in that word we tranſlate <hi>teach</hi> or <hi>make Diſciples,</hi> and not to <hi>Nations.</hi> This we utterly deny, and affirm on the contrary, that it muſt refer to <hi>Nations</hi> and not to <hi>Diſciples,</hi> and that for two Reaſons.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Becauſe we ought to keep to the literal and plain Grammatical Conſtruction of Scriptures, where there is no neceſſary reaſon why we ſhould depart therefrom. Now according to the literal and plain Grammatical Conſtruction of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>[Them]</hi> muſt be referred to <hi>[Nations],</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we tranſlate that word to <hi>teach,</hi> or <hi>Nations,</hi> or <hi>make all Nations Diſciples, baptizing them;</hi> baptizing, who? why, according to the literal Conſtruction of the words, the <hi>Nations</hi> to be taught or made Diſciples; and here is no reaſon why we ſhould depart from the literal and plain Grammatical Conſtruction of the words. But,</p>
                        <p n="2">2. It is altogether doubtful whether our Lord Chriſt in this Commiſſion had any reſpect to ſuch a
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:60484:42"/>Criticiſm as this, <hi>viz.</hi> That Diſciples are included in that word we tranſlate to <hi>teach.</hi> Now to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from the literal and plain Grammatical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, when there is no reaſon ſo to do, upon the Suppoſition of a Criticiſm; in a word, when it is utterly uncertain, whether our Lord Chriſt had any reſpect to any ſuch Criticiſm or no, is unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and ſubjects all Scriptures to be framed into any form, according to the various Fancies of Men: So that undoubtedly they are the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> that are to be baptized.</p>
                        <p>And as for what is ſaid to give Countenance to this Suppoſition, it ſignifies nothing at all. For,</p>
                        <p n="1">1. Whereas it is ſaid, Thus to expound this Text agrees with what is recorded of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>he made Diſciples,</hi> and by his Diſciples <hi>bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them;</hi> this is of no weight, for though he <hi>made Diſciples, and baptized them,</hi> viz. by his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; yet it is not ſaid, he only baptized them he made, or might make Diſciples, and order them to be baptized, and with them their Children or Houſholds.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. Whereas it is yet further ſaid, that thus to expound this Scripture ſeems beſt to agree with the words of <hi>Mark,</hi> recording the ſame Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And anſwerably, that that Clauſe in <hi>Mark, Go preach the Goſpel to every Creature,</hi> anſwers this Clauſe in <hi>Matthew, Go teach all Nations;</hi> and the next Clauſe in <hi>Mark, He that believeth, and is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> anſwers this other Clauſe in <hi>Matthew, Baptizing them.</hi> And conſequently, that the Subjects of Baptiſm muſt be Diſciples, and thoſe Diſciples muſt be Believers. For anſwer to this, there is no neceſſity that we ſhould take theſe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:60484:43"/>ſeveral Clauſes, as anſwering one another; we may conjoin both the words of <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and take the Commiſſion as given out by Chriſt in more words thus: <hi>Go, teach all Nations, baptizing them,</hi> I ſay, <hi>Go, preach the Goſpel to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature: he that believeth, and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved; but he that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</hi> And then as in <hi>Matthew</hi> that Phraſe <hi>[all Nations]</hi> expounds that Clauſe in <hi>Mark, [every Creature];</hi> ſo in that following Clauſe <hi>Mark</hi> only ſhews what ſhould be the Iſſue of their Adminiſtration of theſe two Ordinances of Preaching and Baptizing, not at all determining the Subjects of the one or the other: as for thoſe that did believe, and were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, they ſhould be ſaved; but as for others that believe not, they ſhould be damned, whether bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized or no.</p>
                        <p n="3">3. Whereas it is yet further ſaid, That in caſe we refer <hi>[them]</hi> to the <hi>Nations</hi> to be taught, and not to <hi>Diſciples,</hi> without any limitation, then this Commiſſion would warrant the Baptiſm of all Nations, or all Perſons in every Nations, whether they are taught or no, which to affirm is abſurd.</p>
                        <p>But to this the Anſwer is at hand, That the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections about the Adminiſtration of both theſe Ordinances, left in other Scriptures, ſufficiently prevent that Inconvenience.</p>
                        <p>Now this firſt Suppoſition being utterly ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and falſe, the other Suppoſitions fall with it, and are of no uſe as to the end intended in them. For as for the <hi>2d. Whether Infants are, or can in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of Speech be called Diſciples?</hi> It matters not, ſeeing they are not Diſciples, but the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whoſe Baptiſm is warranted and required in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:60484:43"/>this Commiſſion. And as for the <hi>3d. That this Commiſſion is to be underſtood as excluding all from Baptiſm, that are not comprehended in it:</hi> Suppoſe it ſhould be granted, yet it makes not againſt Infants Baptiſm, ſeeing they are not excluded out of it, but rather included in it, as part of the Nations to be baptized. But becauſe the Suppoſition is falſe in it ſelf, for ſome may be baptized, and that by virtue of this Commiſſion, who are not in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Terms comprehended in it, as will appear in the Anſwer to the Objection, as raiſed by others. And therefore,</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II.</head>
                     <p>Others argue againſt Infant-Baptiſm,
<list>
                           <item>1. From the plain Order (as they expreſs it) laid down by our Lord Chriſt in this Commiſſion, and according to this Order (as they ſuppoſe) theſe two Ordinances of Preaching and Baptizing, ought to be univerſally adminiſtred, and this Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is, that Men ſhould be taught the Doctrine of Faith.</item>
                           <item>2. That being ſo taught, they ſhould be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</item>
                           <item>3. That they ſhould, in the School or Church whereof they are then made Members, be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in every thing elſe they ought to learn. Hence it is concluded, that none but ſuch as are taught, and by teaching made Diſciples, ought to be baptized, and conſequently no Infants.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <div type="answer">
                        <p>In Anſwer unto which we lay down three Concluſions.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. That notwithſtanding this Order in which the Commiſſion is laid down, yet it doth not (as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:60484:44"/>taken abſolutely in its ſelf) neceſſarily exclude In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants from Baptiſm. This is proved two ways,
<list>
                              <item>1. From the general Acknowledgment of our Oppoſers themſelves.</item>
                              <item>2. This is evident in it ſelf, becauſe as there is no mention of Infants, ſo no Word, Phraſe, or Expreſſion, that can rationally be interpreted as neceſſarily excluding them. All that can be ſaid to this is, <hi>That our Lord Chriſt not mentioning Infants together with the Order here laid down for the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Baptiſm, is ſufficient Ground to conclude that they are excluded.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>But to that I anſwer, That this is no ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Ground to conclude that they are excluded. This is undeniably evident from a twofold Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
                        <p n="1">1. It is poſſible that Chriſt may have given out this Commiſſion only with reference to grown Perſons, and hath revealed his Will concerning the Baptiſm of Infants in other parts of his Word. Yet let none ſay, as Mr. <hi>H.</hi> has done, that I grant that he has given out this Commiſſion only with reference to the Adult. I only ſay, it is poſſible he might have done it; and that is enough to prove, that the Commiſſion as abſolutely taken doth not exclude Infants.</p>
                        <p n="2">2. That our Lord Chriſt might, as it is certain he did not, intend this Commiſſion as a full Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for his Apoſtles and Miniſters in the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of theſe two ordinances. And that our Lord Chriſt did not intend that this Commiſſion of it ſelf ſhould be fully and abſolutely directive of the Apoſtles and Miniſters in the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of either of theſe Ordinances, is paſt all ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:60484:44"/>queſtioning, becauſe there are many Queſtions referring to the execution of it, which cannot be determined from the Commiſſion it ſelf, but muſt be determined from other Scriptures, as for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<list>
                              <item>(1.) How the Nations ſhould be diſcipled? whether only by teaching them, or by baptizing them?</item>
                              <item>(2.) Who among the Nations, or who among thoſe to whom the Goſpel ſhould be preached, were to be accounted Diſciples, and anſwerably to be baptized?</item>
                              <item>(3.) Whether the Nations ſhould be baptized as Diſciples, or as Men.</item>
                              <item>(4.) After what manner Baptiſm ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, whether by dipping, or by pouring water upon the Face, or the like? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>(5.) Whether Males, or both Males and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males, ought to be baptized?</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                        <p>And our Oppoſers themſelves are forc'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to other Scriptures for the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe five Queſtions: And why we may not do the like for the reſolution of this Queſtion, Whether only grown Perſons, or they and their Infants, ought to be baptized? no rational account can be given.</p>
                        <p>Now this Commiſſion not being intended, as theſe Inſtances undeniably prove that it was not, as a full Direction to the Apoſtles or Miniſters of the Goſpel for the adminiſtration of this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; it will undeniably follow, that it doth not exclude, but on the other hand may include the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Infants. And if any ſhall ſay, Sure if it had been the Will of out Lord Chriſt that Infants ſhould
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:60484:45"/>been baptized, he would have expreſly declared it in this Commiſſion. In anſwer to ſuch I would ſay, it was far more neceſſary, that ſeeing it was his will that Females as well as Males ſhould be baptized, he ſhould have expreſly declared that; then though it be his will that Infants ſhould be baptized, he ſhould have declared that, yet we ſee he did not; it is enough that he has declared his Will both as to the one and the other in other parts of his Word. But for the further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Doubt, I ſhall lay down a ſecond Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Concl.</hi> 2. That ſeeing our Lord Chriſt hath ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently declared his Will in other parts of his Word, both as to the Covenant-Intereſt of the Infant-Seed of his People, and their Right to the Seal and Token thereof, it was no way neceſſary he ſhould particularly mention that in this Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and the Commiſſion, though it mentions them not, yet doth ſufficiently warrant their Baptiſm. For the clearing up and illuſtration of this, let theſe two Suppoſitions be put, Firſt, that had God ſent his Prophets, or any of them, under the Firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtration, to preach the Goſpel as then revealed to the Gentiles, or any Nation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: Secondly, That he had continued Circumciſion under the Goſpel-Adminiſtration, as the Token of the Covenant; either of which he might have done, had it pleaſed him. Now I would ask any rational Man, Whether this very Commiſſion, only ſubſtituting Circumciſion in the room of Baptiſm, had not been ſufficient to have warranted the Circumciſion of Infants as well as of grown Perſons, though they had not been expreſly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:60484:45"/>mentioned; yea, whether it would have been at all neceſſary that they ſhould have been mentioned? And why the bare Change of the Token of the Covenant ſhould make it neceſſary that Infants ſhould be mentioned in the Commiſſion, no Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be given.</p>
                        <p>To make this yet more plain, Suppoſe our Lord Chriſt ſhould have thus expreſt himſelf in this Commiſſion, <hi>Go teach or diſciple all Nations, bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them;</hi> for the Covenant with the Promiſes thereof ſhall be ſtill extended to, and eſtabliſh'd with both Jews and Gentiles, and their Children together with them, as it was of old with the Jews. I ſay, had he thus expreſt himſelf, he had not come much ſhort of mentioning Infants; why, let but the Scriptures formerly mentioned be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together, 'tis all one as if he had ſo expreſt himſelf.</p>
                        <p>And if any ſhall yet ſay, That if Infants are baptized, then the Order in the Commiſſion is croſs'd. I anſwer, The Commiſſion is not croſs'd, while only the Rules, that our Lord Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath left for the guiding of his Miniſters in the execution of it, are obſerved. But for the full ſatisfaction of this Doubt, we lay down the laſt Concluſion; and therefore,</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Conc.</hi> 3. That notwithſtanding it is the Will of our Lord Chriſt, that Infants ſhould be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, yet it was rational, yea neceſſary, that he ſhould have expreſſed himſelf in the Commiſſion in the order he hath done. For that,
<list>
                              <item>(1.) Conſider what was the State or Condition of the Nations to whom the Apoſtles were now ſent, they were in a ſtate of Darkneſs and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance:
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:60484:46"/>hence the preaching of the Goſpel antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, was abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary.</item>
                              <item>(2.) Conſider the gradual Procedure the Goſpel ſhould, and anſwerably hath made in ſubduing the Nations unto Chriſt. There always have been, and ſtill are ſome Nations to be <hi>diſcipled,</hi> and <hi>brought home</hi> to Chriſt; and all Attempts to diſciple them, and bring them to Chriſt, muſt be by preaching the Goſpel to them, the Diſcipleſhip of Parents ſtill preparing the way to their own and their Childrens Baptiſm.</item>
                              <item>(3.) Conſider, that when Nations are diſcipled, yet the preaching of the Goſpel hath a precedency to the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm; the Seed of Believers baptized in their Infancy muſt be taught, and thereby brought to a ſincere embracement and performance of the Condition of the Covenant, to which as the Seed of ſuch Parents they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore received, in order to their conveying unto their Children, Right to the Covenant, and to Baptiſm as the Seal and Token thereof.</item>
                           </list>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="objection">
                  <head>Object. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Some may further Object,</hi> The Inconſiſtency of ſuch things, as are in the Scriptures declared to have attended the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, and are affirmed of, and required from ſuch as were bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in Primitive Times, with the Doctrine and Practice of Infant-Baptiſm; and for this ſuch Scriptures as theſe, <hi>viz. 1 Cor. 12.13, 14. Epheſ. 4.16. Gal. 3.26, 27.</hi> are alledged.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>The Objection is eaſily removed by a threefold Conſideration.</p>
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:60484:46"/>
                     <p n="1">1. That what is declared of, or required from thoſe that are Members of the viſible Church, of are to be incorporated thereinto by Baptiſm, in theſe and the like Scriptures, agrees to, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually concerns the Church, and the ſeveral Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof in all Ages; hence it may as well be concluded from theſe Scriptures, that Infants ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were, nor ever ſhall be admitted into the Church or viſible Body of Chriſt, the contrary whereunto is evident paſt all poſſible exception, as that in Primitive Times they were not, or now are not to be incorporated into that Body by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Conſider, that it is a thing of frequent occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in Scripture, for things to be ſpoken of, or to whole Bodies or Societies, and that in the moſt univerſal and indefinite Terms, which yet are to be underſtood variouſly, with reſpect to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars according to their reſpective Capacities and Concernments therein. That Speech of <hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Whole Congregation of Iſrael</hi> furniſhment us with ſufficient Inſtances for the proof of this, ſee <hi>Deut. 29th</hi> and <hi>30th Chapters.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. Conſider, That the Scriptures were written, not for the uſe of Infants in their pure Infant-ſtate, but for the uſe of grown Perſons, and that the Deſign of the Holy Ghoſt in the Scriptures mentioned, is to inſtruct and eſtabliſh them in ſome neceſſary Truth, or excite to ſome neceſſary Duty; and anſwerably what is ſpoken in thoſe forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned places only, concerns ſuch Perſons as are capable of receiving ſuch Inſtructions, and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch Duties; but that proves not that Infants are not of, or to be admitted into the Church
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:60484:47"/>or viſible Body of Chriſt by Baptiſm.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="objection">
                  <head>Object. 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Others object,</hi> the Apoſtles Doctrine, taken in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the Primitive Practice. <hi>Say they,</hi> The Apoſtles in their Doctrine did teach, that <hi>Believers ſhould be baptized,</hi> and there is no mention of their teaching that <hi>Infants ſhould be baptized.</hi> So we read of many Believers baptized, but of no Inſtance of any one Infant that was baptized; and therefore ſure Infant-Baptiſm cannot be according to the mind and will of Jeſus Chriſt, but muſt be a Practice introduced into the Church by Men.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>To this four things may be ſaid,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. That the Apoſtles did teach, that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Salvation</hi> doth belong, and conſequently the Covenant in which the Promiſe is contained, muſt needs extend to the <hi>Houſes of Believers,</hi> and that as ſuch, without conſideration had to the Faith and Repentance of any in or of their Houſes.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. That they did exhort Perſons to <hi>be baptized</hi> upon the account of the Promiſes belonging unto them, and this is all one as if they had expreſly taught that Infants ſhould be baptized. It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, that the Infants of Believers are of their Houſes, and being ſo, muſt needs be under the Promiſe of Salvation. Now if one may be baptized upon the account of Intereſt in the Promiſe, any other may be ſo alſo; ſo that they did teach what amounts to as much as if they had in expreſs Terms taught that Infants ſhould be baptized.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. That the Apoſtles did baptize whole Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, and ſometimes ſuch as in which we read not of the Converſion of any, excepting the chief
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:60484:47"/>Heads and Governours only, and in which there is the greateſt probability that there were ſome Infants, at leaſt ſome in their Youth or Childhood, who cannot rationally be ſuppoſed to be baptized on the account of their own perſonal Faith and Repentance. Which taken in conjunction with the two foregoing Particulars, makes it vaſtly more probable that they did baptize ſome Infants, than the Scriptures not expreſly recording their Baptiſm, makes it probable that they did not baptize any.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. That the Scriptures not expreſly recording that the Apoſtles did either teach or practiſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm, is no proof that they did not do both. Many things that the Apoſtles taught and practiſed, are not recorded in Scripture, as it is ſaid of Chriſt, <hi>He taught in his Doctrine, and did many things which are not written;</hi> the like may be ſaid of the Apoſtles. It is ſufficient that the Scriptures in general declare the whole Mind and Will of God concerning the Faith and Practice of his Church and People, though it be not recorded. That ſome of the Penmen did teach and practiſe every Duty appertaining thereunto, that the grand Promiſes of the Covenant appertain to the Seed of Believers, and that all to whom thoſe Promiſes do appertain ought to have the Token of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant applied to them, is ſufficiently evident throughout the Scriptures, both in the Old and New Teſtament. Hence, though it be not record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in expreſs Terms, that the Apoſtles did either teach or practiſe Infant-Baptiſm, yet we may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conclude they did both.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="objection">
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:60484:48"/>
                  <head>Object. 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Laſtly, It is farther Objected by ſome,</hi> That In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Baptiſm cannot be according to the Mind and Will of Chriſt, becauſe of their Incapability of the Ends and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes of Baptiſm.</p>
                  <div type="answer">
                     <head>Anſwer.</head>
                     <p>It is ſufficient that they are capable of ſome, at leaſt the main and chief Ends and Uſes of Baptiſm. It is no way neceſſary, that every one to whom ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Circumciſion of old was, or Baptiſm now is to be applied, ſhould be capable of all the Ends and Uſes of the one or the other. Who dare deny, yea, or queſtion, but that our Lord Chriſt may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the Application of Baptiſm to Infants, as capable of ſome of the Ends and Uſes of it, though uncapable of others; and that they are capable of ſome, yea, the main and chief Ends and Uſes of Baptiſm, is and muſt be granted on all hands. Hence their Incapability of ſome of the Ends and uſes of it, makes nothing at all againſt their Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p>Now then our three Propoſitions being (as we ſee they are) firmly eſtabliſhed, by the unanimous Suffrage both of the Old and New-Teſtament, and all Objections of weight that may be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the one or the other of them being removed, we are ſafely led by them to our main Concluſion, viz. <hi>That it is the Will of our Lord Chriſt, that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant Seed of Believers ſhould be baptized.</hi> They are under the Covenant, as having the main Promiſes of it appertaining to them, and anſwerably ought to have the Token thereof applied to them.</p>
                     <p>And as a Cloſe of all, what remains, but that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:60484:48"/>as Believers maintain, and cheerfully proceed on in that Practice; ſo both they, and their Children, as growing up to years of maturity, do well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove theſe great Priviledges, which God of his abundant Grace and Mercy hath granted unto them. Which that they may do, I have in a third Tract, according to Divine Aſſiſtance given in, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the reſolution of four Queſtions, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. What are the Reaſons of God's appointed the Application of the Token of the Covenant to the Infant-Seed of his People?</item>
                        <item>2. What are the Benefits and Advantages accru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them thereby.</item>
                        <item>3. What is the Duty of Parents towards their Children, as bearing the Token of the Covenant.</item>
                        <item>4. What Improvement Children may and ought to make of the Token of the Covenant, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to them in their Infancy, as they grow up to years of maturity.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>In the reſolution of all which Queſtions, I have ſtudied both brevity and plainneſs; neither do I ſee how what hath been ſaid, could be well contract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into a narrower room, without prejudice to the Ends aimed at, the whole being but as it were an Epitomy of what may ſeem neceſſary to be ſpoken, conſidering the weight and importance of thoſe Queſtions; nor do I know well how to expreſs my ſelf, <hi>conſideratis conſiderandis,</hi> with more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs than I have done, nor am I as yet made ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that any thing propoſed or aſſerted in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the one or the other of them, needs a further Confirmation than what it already hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:60484:49"/>That which is moſt doubtful, ſo far as I yet underſtand, at leaſt to Paedobaptiſts, to whom (as well as to Antipaedobaptiſts) I had a reſpect in that Treatiſe, is, Whether all thoſe Benefits and Priviledges, that in the reſolution of the ſecond Queſtion I have aſſigned to the Infant-Seed of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, do really and truly appertain unto them, or only in <hi>foro Eccleſiae,</hi> or in viſible appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance? To whom I would only ſay, That in caſe the Covenant is enter'd with, and the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes thereof made to them definitely, that is, with and to each of them in particular; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that all thoſe Benefits and Priviledges are granted, and do belong to them univerſally, or to every one of them in particular, as in caſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes be made to them definitely, they muſt needs do; it will neceſſarily follow, that they are grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and do appertain to them in reality and truth, as well as in outward appearance. Granting the former, there is no more juſt reaſon to queſtion the latter, than there would be, ſuppoſing a Man were known and granted to be a true Believer, yet to queſtion whether all this Good, or all theſe Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and Priviledges do appertain to him in reality and truth or no, ſeeing as they are the Seed of true Believers, ſuch as are Believers not only in the ſight of Men, but the ſight of God, that I ſpeak of.</p>
                     <p>So the Covenant is entred with, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of it, made to them meerly as the Seed of ſuch Parents, without reſpect had to any Qualifications in, or any Conditions to be performed by them. Whence, ſuppoſing we grant the Covenant is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred with, and the Promiſes thereof made to them definitely, or with and to each of them in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:60484:49"/>in caſe we either queſtion, whether all that Good, and all thoſe Benefits and Priviledges are granted, and do appertain to them univerſally; or whether ſuppoſing we grant that, yet queſtion whether they are granted and do appertain to them in reality and truth; it muſt be either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we queſtion whether all that Good, and all thoſe Benefits and Priviledges are contained in theſe Promiſes of the Covenant appertaining to them; or becauſe we queſtion whether God be faithful in his Promiſes, that is, do indeed and in truth grant unto, or confer upon thoſe to whom the Promiſes do appertain, what Good is really and truly contained in them. Either of which things why we ſhould rather queſtion in reſpect of Infants, than grown Perſons, no rational account can be given. And to queſtion, much more to deny the one or the other, has a direct tendency to overthrow the Faith and Comfort of all Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and render the Covenant of Grace with the various Promiſes of it utterly inſignificant, and of no uſe unto Men. Indeed that which ſeems to cauſe ſome to haeſitate about, and keeps them from a ready Compliance with what I have affirmed, is a Suppoſition, that the Caſe of Infants is the ſame with, at leaſt like unto the Caſe of grown Perſons; becauſe grown Perſons may viſibly appear to be in Covenant, and have the Promiſes thereof appertaining unto them, and conſequently to have all that Good, or all thoſe Benefits and Priviledges granted to and conferred upon them, when yet neither the Covenant, nor the Promiſes of it, do indeed appertain to them in the ſight of God, and conſequently none of that Good, or of thoſe Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:60484:50"/>and Priviledges do appertain to them in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and truth. They are ready to think it may be ſo with Infants. But now the Caſe of grown Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and of Infants in this matter is wholly different; the Intereſt of grown Perſons in the Covenant and Promiſes of it, depends upon their own Performance of the <hi>Conditions of the Covenant;</hi> but it is otherwiſe with the Infant-Seed of Believers, they have their Intereſt in the Covenant purely from the Promiſe, as made to them as the Seed of believing Parents. Hence, ſuppoſe that Parents are true Believers, their Seed muſt needs have a like Intereſt in the Covenant that they themſelves have, and the ſame Good, or the ſame Benefits and Priviledges muſt needs be granted to, and conferred upon their Seed, that are given unto and conferred upon themſelves. Now that the Covenant is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed entred with, and the Promiſes thereof made to the Infant-ſeed of Believers definitely, I have (as I conceive) ſufficiently proved. And I had intended to have ſomewhat further en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged and ſtrengthned theſe Reaſons already offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and alſo to have added ſomewhat more for the Confirmation of that their definite and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Intereſt in the Covenant, and Promiſes of it; But not having as yet met with any Objections againſt thoſe Reaſons already offered, I ſhall for brevity ſake forbear, and only ſay to the ſincere Enquirer after the Mind of God in theſe things, <hi>Conſider what hath been ſaid, and the Lord give thee <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding in all things.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="open_letter">
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:60484:50"/>
            <head>To the Godly and Learned among the <hi>Antipaedo-baptiſts,</hi> eſpecially the Authors of the late Confeſſion of their Faith.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend and beloved Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Deſign of the preceding Sheets being to lay level with ordinary Capacities, what I have already made publick in a Method more ſuting Scholaſtick Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the adjoining an Addreſs unto you may juſtly be deemed improper. That I may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do both you and my ſelf right, I ſhall give you a brief account of my thus doing. Far be it from me once to imagine, that the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Tracts, or any thing in them (a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capitulation of which this is) is unto you unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible. I doubt not but that at leaſt (will you make uſe of thoſe Abilities, both natural and acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you are ſo plentifully furniſhed with) you can take a proſpect of what I have ſaid from firſt to laſt, and by comparing one thing with another, paſs a judgment upon the whole. It is true, to note in one paſſage, thoſe two, (<hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and Mr. <hi>D L.</hi>) who have ſeen meet to take notice of what I have written, ſeem to complain of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:60484:51"/>as though I had neither ſet down my Theſis diſtinctly, nor proſecuted my Arguments ſyllogiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally, at leaſt in a form intelligible to all Perſons. But I am perſwaded their Complaints had their riſe from ſome other Cauſe, and not from any difficulty themſelves found; and whether I had any reaſon to take any notice of the former's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, or the latter, to object it as a Failure in me that I did not, I ſhall leave with you to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not deny, but that the Method I have proceeded in hath render'd thoſe Diſcourſes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what obſcure to Capacities unacquainted with the Rules of Logical Argumentation, neither was I without ſome previous Intimations that it would ſo do; yet was not I thereby diſcouraged from the publication of them; my main deſign being, by the rectifying ſome <hi>Miſtakes</hi> I ſaw ſome of the chief Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerters of Infant-Baptiſm lay under, and the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome few Arguments overlook'd by them, to eſtabliſh more fully that Practice in the Minds of the Learned; wherein what ſucceſs I have had, or yet may have, through the Bleſſing of God upon my weak endeavours, I ſhall leave to the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of others, and the diſcovery of Time. This I can through Grace ſay, I have not as yet ſeen any Cauſe to repent, either of the Pains I have taken, or the Charges I have been at; neither had I any cauſe to fear that I ſhould willingly, or could be juſtly ſuſpected deſignedly, through any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound Mediums, or fallacious Reaſonings, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote an Error, while I deſigned to eſtabliſhed the Truth. I was well aſſured there were thoſe of your Perſwaſion, who could ſufficiently underſtand
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:60484:51"/>me, and were able to detect both the unſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my Mediums, and Fallaciouſneſs of my Arguments, had the one or the other been ſo: but no Attempt of that Nature has as yet been made by any. But to return, this I was ſaying, It is far from me to imagine, that what I have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy written is to you unintelligible: Let not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my adding this Addreſs to you to this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium</hi> be offenſive, either to you or any others, as though't were a reflection upon your Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: but three things have induced me hereunto.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Encouragement you have given me in your late <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> and <hi>Appendix</hi> thereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, and that not only by your Orthodoxy in the main Doctrines of the Goſpel, but more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by that Diſcovery you have there made of your Love to the Truth, Moderation of Spirit, and being through the anointing of the Spirit not only ſhewn but led into that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, recommended in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. to us by the holy Apoſtle of the Gentiles. It is indeed hard for any <hi>reciprocare ſerram</hi> in Polemical Divinity, eſpecially in that dawning Light we are yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, without being in one reſpect or another, if not really,<note place="margin">Solent Injuriae illis prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare ſuffragium, quibus ſtudium eſt non de verit ate ſed proprià gloriari victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riâ; in his autem qui to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ Intentione cupiunt de compertâ veritate gaudire locum hac penitus non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. <hi>Maxent.</hi> Dialog. contra <hi>Neſtorian.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> yet in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, injurious one to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Now when it is not Love to Truth, but Deſire of Victory, that keeps up the Conteſt, theſe Injuries, whether real or ſuppoſed, will ordinarily be more heeded than the Arguments urged: but when Love to Truth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:60484:52"/>eſpecially if attended with thoſe other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fruits of the Spirit, Moderation and Charity, as Plain-dealing will not be reputed injurious, ſo even that which may be really judged to be ſo, will be overlook'd and paſſed by. Which things I having more abundant Ground to hope are true of you, I cannot but promiſe my ſelf, that as what I ſhall ſay, though it be with much freedom of Speech, ſhall meet with a candid Interpretation, yea, and a kind Reception from you; ſo in caſe any thing injurious ſhould unwittingly (for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly there ſhall not) drop from my Pen, that ſhall be no Let to your more through weighing the Arguments I have offered, or embracement of Truth, ſo far as by them it is demonſtrated.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That in caſe any of you ſhall farther appear in the ventilation of this Controverſy, which I would by no means diſcourage you from, you may with more eaſe take a full proſpect of it, at leaſt as managed by me, both as to the Foundations I have laid, and the whole Structure built thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not be put to the trouble of bringing things together, that lay in my former Treatiſes at ſome diſtance one from another, in order to a due comparing them one with another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I may probably here have put my laſt hand to this Controverſy, I am aware of the uncertainty of Life; neither am I (ſuppoſing God ſhould leng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then out that) altogether without hope that the addition of any thing more in purſuance of it will be utterly unneceſſary; the Reaſons of this my Hope will more fully appear before I take my leave of you.</p>
            <p>And now, Brethren, having given you this brief
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:60484:52"/>Account, both negatively and poſitively, of my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>theſe Lines</hi> to you to the foregoing <hi>Copendium,</hi> bear with me, though I ſay to you, as <hi>Elihu</hi> to <hi>Job, I am ful of matter, the Spirit within me conſtraineth me; I muſt ſpeak, that I may be refreſhed; and let me I pray you</hi> (as he there adds) <hi>not accept any Mans perſon.</hi> I ſpeak to you as Friends, yea, as Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as Joint-heirs with us of the common Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, purchaſed by our Lord Chriſt both for you and us. Hence, ad Plainneſs of Speech moſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes me, ſo to you (I hope) it will neither be offenſive nor grievous. Your Orthodoxy and Soundneſs of Judgment in the main Fundamental Doctrines of the Goſpel, with that Love to Truth, Moderation of Spirit, and Chriſtian Charity, afore taken notice of, appearing in your late Confeſſion, and Appendix thereunto annexed, are greatly commendable; and I hope I may truly ſay, they have endeared you, not only unto me, but to all that love our Lord Chriſt in ſincerity: neither ſhall you (as I hope) at any time find me in Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours after mutual Love, Converſation, and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Communion, in things wherein we are agreed, in the Rear, as you have ſtill done in theſe unpleaſing Conteſts. For though I would, and dare do no leſs than<note n="*" place="margin">Quia inextricabile quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dammodò malum nan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam deſinit humana cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da pulſare, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> inopinatis argumentis fidem inquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Catholicam, neceſſe eſt Sectatoribus verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis prudenter captioſas ejus ſententias praevidere, ſapientér<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> detegere, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latás<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in medium malleo veritatis cohibere, &amp; uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ad effuſionem ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis contra eas pro verstate certare. Ibid. praef.</note> manifeſt a true Zeal in maintaining the Truth; yet that through Grace ſhall be no Let to me in an amicable and peaceable
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:60484:53"/>walking with you according to what we have jointly attained unto. I have of a long time been, and ſtill am wholly perſwaded, that thoſe Aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of affections, and Diſtances in point of Chriſtian Converſation and Communion in things wherein they all agree, found among Chriſtians, holding the Head, and ſincerely embracing and practiſing the Truth as it is in Jeſus, according to the meaſures of Light they have reſpectively re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, are utterly diſſonant from the Doctrine of our Lord Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and the Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Primitive Practice. And ſurely, might we be ſo happy, as to take true meaſures of thoſe Differences that are between us, and manage them with that Spirit of Moderation and mutual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance that the Goſpel requires, it would not only not a little conduce to our mutual Edification and Comfort, but greatly obviate thoſe Offences taken at them by the Men of the World. Grace never ſhines more brightly, nor appears with a greater luſtre, than when it is duly exerciſed under viſible Diſadvantages. Hence if that mutual Love of Chriſtians (when yet thinking the ſame thing) appeared ſo beautiful in the eyes of the Heathens, that they could not behold it without an, <hi>Ecce quam mutuò ſe amant:</hi> much more would it ſo do, when it is kept up under the diſadvantages of ſome Differences both in judgment and Practice. And hence the Diſadvantages Religion may lie under through the Differences in Judgment and Practice among the more ſtrict Profeſſors of it, would be abundantly recompenſed through the Illuſtriouſneſs of their Grace, rendred more beautiful by occaſion of them. And hence, as I cannot but greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:60484:53"/>in you that Goſpel-becoming Frame of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit you have diſcovered; ſo you may aſſure your ſelves, I ſhall through Divine Aſſiſtance always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to maintain and promote the like, both in my ſelf, and all others walking in the ſame ſteps with me, according as opportunity is put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands.</p>
            <p>But Brethren, though I cannot but in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs commend what appears in you ſo greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable; yet I muſt, and that alſo in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to you, ſhew you wherein I cannot but judge you blame-worthy. I remember what the Comick ſaith, <hi>Aſſentatores non veniunt ut arrideant, ſed ut ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodant.</hi> Flattery, however it may pleaſe, yet is prejudicial. Two things more eſpecially I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but judge blame-worthy in you:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That when you come to give the Reaſons why you cannot acquieſce in what (as you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs) is urged by us againſt you, or (as you elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where candidly interpret) is offered for your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, you wholly overlook thoſe Scriptures and Scripture-Arguments, that we, at leaſt ſome of us, conceive moſt cogent, and anſwerably are moſt inſiſted on by us, to eſtabliſh our Practice, and convince you of your Miſtakes, and either only ſuppoſe us to reaſon quite otherwiſe than indeed we do, or only ſingle out ſome of thoſe Scriptures and Arguments drawn from them, that we only make uſe of as additional enforcements of our main Arguments, but not as demonſtrative of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſay, you ſuppoſe us to reaſon quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe than indeed we do, or to make uſe of other Mediums than indeed we do. Thus in your
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:60484:54"/>114th and 115th pag. you thus expreſs your ſelves, <hi>That albeit this Covenant-Holineſs &amp; Church-Member<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſhould be, as is ſuppoſed, in reference unto the Infants of Believers; yet no Command for Infant-Baptiſm does immediatly and directly reſult from ſuch a Quality or Relation;</hi> inſinuating thereby as though we ſhould affirm there did, which we do not. So <hi>Pag.</hi> 125. you again thus expreſs your ſelves, <hi>Of whatſoever nature the Holineſs of the Children mentioned,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.12. <hi>be, yet they who do conclude that all ſuch Children (whether Infants or of riper years) have from hence an immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Right to Baptiſm, do (as we conceive) put more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Concluſion, than will be found in the Premiſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas we do not conclude meerly from their Covenant-Holineſs, that they have from thence any immediate Right to Baptiſm; we only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that Scripture as a Confirmation of their Covenant-ſtate, which you at preſent deny not, neither will you determine of what Holineſs the Apoſtle there ſpeaks; ſo that as you grant not, ſo you deny not but the Apoſtle may ſpeak of foede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Holineſs, which is all that we affirm. Hence what you ſubjoin in thoſe 114 and 115 <hi>pages,</hi> ſo in 125, and onwards to 129, is utterly impertinent. We ſay not that a Command for Infant-Baptiſm doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly and directly reſult from their Intereſt in the Covenant, or Church-Memberſhip; but this we ſay, that God having graciouſly extended his Covenant to them, hath been pleaſed of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign will and pleaſure to annex a Command, that the Token of his Covenant (whatever that ſhould be) ſhould be kept both by Parents and Children, which Token of the Covenant we ſay was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion under the firſt Teſtament, but now is Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:60484:54"/>And beſides, there are other Arguments which you cannot certainly be unacquainted with, which do (ſuppoſing that their Foederal Holineſs and Church-Memberſhip) undeniably eſtabliſh the dueneſs and rightfulneſs of their Baptiſm. So that (I conceive) you cannot poſſibly, grant their Foederal Holineſs and Church-Memberſhip, but you muſt grant their Baptiſm. Now for you to overlook all theſe Arguments, and fain us to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue quite otherwiſe than indeed we do, (or if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly any have done, yet their Miſtakes have been rectified) is (to ſay no more) matter of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. The reaſons of your ſo doing muſt be left with your ſelves; yet I cannot but tell you that ſuch Dealings have a ſad tendency to obſtruct that good Deſign, <hi>viz.</hi> the Reconciliation of our mutual Love each to other, which you ſeem to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on. It will beget a kind of Suſpicion in the minds of Men, that you too wilfully ſhut your Eyes againſt that Light that is held forth unto you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, You only ſingle out ſome of thoſe Scriptures and Arguments drawn from them, that we make uſe of as additional Enforcements, but not as demonſtrative of themſelves. Thus for thoſe Inſtances of whole Families being baptized, we only improve them as a further Confirmation of our main Arguments, but not as demonſtrative as of themſelves, and that upon ſuppoſition of the foederal Holineſs and Church-Memberſhip of the <hi>Infant-Seed</hi> of Believers, and the validity of thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments we have urged for their Baptiſm upon that Suppoſition. That theſe Inſtances may be taken in as additional Confirmations of our Practice, I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily perſwaded your ſelves will not deny. So that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:60484:55"/>alas! Brethren, what a ſlender account have you given us of the Reaſons of your non-acquieſcence in what is urged by us againſt you. No wonder if you ſo greatly miſtake us on the one hand, and on the other hand overlook our main Arguments, and then only take notice of what Scriptures and Arguments we make uſe of only as additional Confirmations, though you cannot comply with our practice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That which I cannot but judge alike blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in you, is your too evident Partiality. This is ſo apparent in you Citation of, and Remark upon Dr. <hi>Lightfoot</hi>'s Interpretation of that <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. that it is a wonder your ſelves ſhould not ſee it. The Doctor conceives that Circumciſion is there ſaid to be a <hi>Seal</hi> not meerly (for in ſome ſence he grants it might be) <hi>of that Righteouſneſs</hi> Abraham <hi>had while in his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncircumciſion;</hi> but more eſpecially of that Righteouſneſs which his uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Seed, that is, believing Gentiles, ſhould have when they ſhould come to imitate his Faith. Now you conceive that this is ſo evidently the true ſence and meaning of the Apoſtle in that place, that it is impertinent for any to alledge that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to prove that Circumciſion was a Seal of the Righteouſneſs of Faith, either to <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, or to any of his circumciſed Poſterity. But Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, let me prevail with you ſeriouſly to weight theſe few things, which I ſhall but as it were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to your conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, that this Interpretation ſeems ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly inconſiſtent with the Apoſtle's deſign and ſcope in that place. The Apoſtle's deſign is to ſhew that <hi>Abraham</hi> both had a Righteouſneſs imputed
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:60484:55"/>to him, and had Circumciſion given him as a Seal thereof, <hi>That he might be the Father of all that ſhould believe, who were of the Circumciſion;</hi> but this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation ſuppoſes him already their Father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly, And rather conſider the utter Improbability, that this is indeed the true ſence and meaning of the Apoſtle; let me ſay, <hi>cum pace tanti viri,</hi> that the Doctor's words are ſo far from having any evidence, as you conceit, that they have not any probability of Truth in them. For,</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Should it be granted, which yet it is not, that Circumciſion might be of this uſe as applied to <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, who was the Father of all that ſhould believe; yet why it ſhould be of the ſame uſe as applied to all his natural Poſterity, as this Interpretation takes it for granted that it was, no reaſon can be imagined. A Seal is for confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ſomewhat to the Parties to whom it is given; now why God by this seal of Circumciſion ſhould confirm to the Jews the Promiſe of juſtifying the Gentiles, through a Righteouſneſs imputed to them upon their believing, when it did not ſeal or confirm the ſame Good to themſelves, is hard to imagine.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Circumciſion is expreſly ſaid to be the <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of that Covenant</hi> eſtabliſhed with <hi>Abraham and his Seed in their Generations;</hi> but now the Imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Righteouſneſs to us Gentiles upon conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our believing, was no Article on God's part in the Covenant, as entred and eſtabliſhed with <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed, at leaſt as ſeverally and particularly conſidered, and as the Covenant was ſo entred with them, Circumciſion was the Token of it. Hence how it could ſeal to them what was
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:60484:56"/>no-where promiſed to them is hard to imagine.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) This Interpretation, at leaſt as you ſeem to take it, ſuppoſes hat the natural Seed of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> though in Covenant, yet had not a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs imputed to them: for how unreaſonable would it be to ſay that Imputation of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Gentiles was ſealed to the Jews, and yet that Righteouſneſs imputed unto them not alike ſealed unto them; that would be to ſay, they had a Good of which they had no Promiſe ſealed to them, and yet that Good of which they had a Promiſe not ſealed to them.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) According to this Interpretation the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle's words can hardly be good ſence, ſeeing the Righteouſneſs of Faith is not a Quality inherent in, but a Relation predicable of thoſe to whom it is imputed; but according to this Interpretation the Apolſte's words muſt run thus, <hi>He received Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, a Seal of the Righteouſneſs which ſhould be in the Circumciſion;</hi> for the words are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) Adde this one thing more, That the very ſame Phraſe in the next verſe is and muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily be render'd as it is by our Tranſlators in this. Now to underſtand the ſame Phraſe after ſuch a different manner in one verſe, from what it muſt neceſſarily be underſtood in the next, when there is no warrant from Scripture, nor any juſt reaſon from the Context ſo to do, is unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Suppoſe we ſhould grant the Doctor's Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation to be right, which you ſee we have no reaſon to do, yet neither is your Cauſe at all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged, nor ours prejudiced thereby, ſeeing he
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:60484:56"/>grants that Circumciſion in ſome ſence was a Seal to <hi>Abraham</hi> of that Righteouſneſs which he had by Faith while in his Uncircumciſion. Now of what uſe it was to him, of the ſame uſe it was to all to whom it was rightfully applied, as I have elſewhere fully proved: Now ſuppoſe it might have a further reſpect, yet that not ways prejudices the Uſe and Improvement we make of the Text for the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Practice. So that I cannot but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonder that you ſhould put ſuch a Remark upon that Interpretation of that Scripture, which ſeems evidently inconſiſtent with the Apoſtle's ſcope, is utterly improbable in it ſelf, and yet is of no uſe to the furthering of your Cauſe, nor makes any head of Oppoſition againſt ours.</p>
            <p>And truly, Brethren, I now begin to leſs won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that you acquieſce not in what is offered by us for your ſatisfaction; it cannot be thought ſtrange that you ſhould continue your Practice different from ours, when you either only ſuppoſe that our Practice is eſtabliſhed by ſuch Arguments as we make no uſe of, or if any haply have made uſe of them, yet they are confeſſed by others of us to be invalid, and in the mean time overlook thoſe Arguments which we conceive to be cogent and demonſtrative, and withal take a Conceit of one ſingle Man, (however Learned, and in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Judicious) that indeed hath no probability of Truth in it, nor really of any uſe to you, to carry ſuch evidence of Truth, as though ſufficient to counter-ballance the Judgments of all others, though at leaſt ſome of them not inferiour unto him either in Learning or Judgment, that are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded; though it is to me matter of no
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:60484:57"/>ſmall Admiration, that you who can with great Judgment examine other controverted Doctrines, and hold faſt that which is good, ſhould ſo do.</p>
            <p>And when I find you thus partial towards this Cauſe you have eſpouſed; wherein I am enforced to appear in oppoſition to you, I have ſome Ground to ſuſpect that what is written by any other in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to what has been offered for your ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or in fayour of your Cauſe, may find that entertainment with you, which otherwiſe ſhould any conſidering what is written ſuppoſe that it would find, you probably would return ſome ſuch Anſwer as <hi>Hazael</hi> returned to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2 Kin. 8.13. And therefore I have judged it not altogether in vain herewith to preſent you with ſome brief Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon a Sheet of Paper not long ſince publiſhed by one Mr. <hi>D'Laune,</hi> making a ſhew of a Confutation of my Books. Indeed had I not ſome Intimations, whether my Information fail me or no I cannot certainly ſay, as though one of no ſmall note among you ſhould ſay, <hi>That</hi> Mr. D Laune <hi>bad performed his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking with a great deal of Reaſon.</hi> or words to that effect, though himſelf had been told, and that by one of no ſmall Judgment in this Controverſy, that Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi>'s Book as to me ſignified not two Straws, I could hardly have imagined, what power ſoever Antici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations and Prejudices may have upon the minds of Men, it could have ſignified any more to any of you. Whether it do at leaſt deſerve to ſignify any thing more, I ſhall now refer to the determination of God's Vice-gerent, I mean Conſcience in you. The Title Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> gives his Papers is, <hi>A brief Survey and Confutation of</hi> Mr. Whiſton's <hi>Books:</hi> but
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:60484:57"/>he hath ſeen meet to aſſault only the firſt, with the Poſtſcript of the laſt, and that at ſuch a vaſt diſtance that I can hardly think (ſetting aſide what he ſaith to the Preface wherein the Controverſy is not directly concerned, and that brief Account that he gives of my Books) had he not mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Name, that any Reader could ever imagine he had any reſpect to my Book, yea, or had ever ſeen or read it, ſo far is he from a Confutation of it. The whole of what he faith hardly makes fourteen Pages, five and a great part of the ſixth of which contains a Confutation (according to his Title) of my Preface, and a brief Account of ſome part of my Book.</p>
            <p>As to what he ſaith to my Preface, of how little ſignification it is I ſhall wholly leave to your Judgments. I ſay not that the Cauſes there aſſigned of the prevailing of your Judgments and Practice, are the Cauſes of all their rejecting the Practice we contend for, and embracing yours, who do reject the one and embrace the other, nor will he (as I ſuppoſe) engage for all of your Perſwaſion, that the Cauſe of their embracing of that Perſwaſion is not the one or the other o the things there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; or if he ſhould, doubtleſs there are not many will believe him to have ſuch acquaintance with the Hearts of Men, as to put any value upon that engagement; but ſuppoſe he could, how is the Cauſe contended for by me prejudiced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? And as for the Digreſſion concerning Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences he falls into upon occaſion of the third Cauſe aſſigned by me, I dare boldly ſay, you know and cannot but acknowledg he perfectly trifles; neither can I imagine any other Reaſon of that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:60484:58"/>(for I ſuppoſe we are fully agreed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Conſequences) except it be to uſher in that Argument he lays down in his third Page, which he would have his Reader believe unanſwerably proves that there is indeed no Birth-Holineſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel-Adminiſtration; but whether it be of any more weight than if he had ſaid, There is none, becauſe there is none, is left to your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. How abſurd is it to jumble together the Covenant-Intereſt or Foederal Holineſs of the Seed of Believers, with things purely Ceremonial? That all Ceremonial Differences between Meats, Birds, Beaſts, and ſo forth, are taken away, we readily grant; but that the Birth-Priviledg of the Seed of Believers was ever founded in that Law, we utterly deny, and affirm on the other hand, that it is founded in the Covenant of Grace, which is one and the ſame in all Ages, nor doth Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> offer the leaſt Proof that it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. So that I ſhall appeal unto Mr. <hi>Delaun</hi>'s own Conſcience, whether in this Argument he did not knowingly and deſinedly paraſyllogize, or put a Fallacy on his unwary Reader?</p>
            <p>Brethren, I muſt tell you plainly, and ſure you cannot but know it, that ſuch Dealings greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon your Party, they will (do Men what they can) beget Prejudices in their Minds, they ſavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo much of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, whereby Men not only of unſound Judgments, but corrupt Minds, lie in wait to deceive. Now then be you your ſelves Judges, to how little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> has ſpent above one third part of his pretended Confutatio of this firſt Books.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:60484:58"/>
            <p>But to come to his Confutation. And thus after the afore-mentioned account he gives of my Book, he thus begins, pag. <hi>6 As to</hi> Mr. Whiſton's <hi>firſt ſubordinate Propoſition, being before rejected, I ſay,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> here tells us he hath rejected my firſt Propoſition, but refers us not to the place where, that we might ſee whether he hath done it upon any rational Grounds or no; nor do I find where he had afore rejected it, much leſs any Reaſon of his ſo doing. As for his following Diſcourſe, that which he drives at in it I ſuppoſe is this, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſhew, <hi>That the Covenant of Grace is ſuch, as that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the natural Seed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>or of any other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents, as ſuch, can have an Intereſt in it, or Right to the Promiſes of it.</hi> And hence he would have his Reader conclude, that this my firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition cannot be true, unleſs ſuppoſing by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant I mean the Covenant of Circumciſion; nor can I rationally make that uſe of that Promiſe for the eſtabliſhing the Practice of Infants Baptiſm that I do. Now let us ſee how he hath performed his Undertaking; in order whereunto I ſhall firſt pare off what is impertinent as to his preſent pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, ſeeing he is now in pretence confuting my Book; and thus his whole Diſcourſe, which takes tip upward of two more of his fourteen Pages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the manner of the Covenant's Adminiſtration, muſt be laid aſide, as that wherein my Book is no way concerned, ſeeing I ſufficiently declare, and certainly Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> could not but know it, that when I affirm the Infant-Seed of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of all other <hi>Believers</hi> are taken with their Parents into the Covenant, I ſtill mean the Covenant it ſelf,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:60484:59"/>and not its outward Adminiſtration; and then to what end and purpoſe he ſhould enlarge ſo much upon the manner of the Covenants Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on remains with himſelf, nothing I have ſaid is at all concerned therein. Now then take the Covenant as conſidered in regard of its Eſſence and Subſtance, and let us ſee,</p>
            <p>Firſt, How far Mr. <hi>De-Laun</hi> and I are agreed, and we evidently agree in two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That God in that Promiſe, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Seed. That Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> agrees with me in this, is evident; for in his <hi>12th pag.</hi> he expreſly grants, that if I mean the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion, as it is called <hi>Acts</hi> 7.8. neither himſelf nor any Body elſe denies this my firſt Propoſition. Now I have ſufficiently decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that that is the Covenant that I mean; and by the Covenant of Circumciſion I mean the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant the Sign or Token of which was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and ſo for ought I know doth Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> too. I confeſs, there is a Paſſage or two in his Papers that ſeem to intimate, that by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Circumciſion he intends Circumciſion it ſelf, or the Command enjoining Circumciſion; but his granting, that if when I ſay that Promiſe of God's being a God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected his natural Seed, I mean the Covenant of Circumciſion, neither he nor any Body elſe denies it, plainly ſhews that he cannot ſo underſtand the Covenant of Circumciſion here, ſeeing that is a Command laid upon <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, and not a Promiſe; and he cannot poſſibly imagine that I ſhould have reſpect to that Command, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I not only ſpeak of a Promiſe, but expreſly
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:60484:59"/>ſhew that it is that very Promiſe <hi>v.</hi> 7. that I have reference unto; ſo that Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> and I are plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed in this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are agreeed in this, <hi>viz.</hi> Either that there are two Covenants, each of which may bear the denomination of the Covenant of Grace, the one abſolute, the other conditional, or elſe that one and the ſame Covenant, uſually called the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, may be diſtinguiſhed of as abſolute or conditional. And that we are agreed in this is evident, becauſe Mr. <hi>D'Laun,</hi> having ſpoken of the abſolute Covenant of Grace, and having affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that this Covenant belongeth not to Infants (as I am far from ſaying that it doth) he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly adds, <hi>The conditional Covenant of Grace, if they will ſo call it,</hi> &amp;c. It may ſeem he would rather have it called a mutual Covenant; but we ſee that he plainly diſtinguiſheth between the ſingle or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Covenant, which he ſaith was made with the Elect, and the mutual or conditional Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which is offered to all, and actually made with Believers as ſuch.</p>
            <p>So that in theſe two things Mr. <hi>D'L.</hi> and I are agreed. And if it be ſaid, wherein then lies the Differences between us?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, I conceive it lies here, That whereas I affirm that this Covenant mentioned <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. was not only a Covenant of Grace, but is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Covenant of Grace, under which Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers always have been, and ſtill are. Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> either holds that it was the old Covenant, which he ſuppoſeth to have been a Covenant of Works, and which is ſaid by the Apoſtle to be vaniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; or elſe that it was a complicated Covenant,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:60484:60"/>both the Covenant of Grace, and alſo the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Works, as he calls it, or the old Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Which Conceit, ſuppoſing either Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> or any others have embraced it, may claim the Primogeniture among all the Abſurdities that have ever dropt from the Pen of any that ever communicated any thing to publick view. That one and the ſame Promiſe ſhould conſtitute both the Covenant of Grace and the Covenant of Works, (as he muſt hold it of one and the ſame Promiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> that mentioned in <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. or he ſpeaks nothing to the purpoſe) is ſo extravagantly abſurd, that it ſeems very harſh to charge any Man with it, unleſs he had in expreſs words affirmed it; yet I much ſuſpect it is Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi>'s Conceit, as well as it was Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>'s before him, but I ſhall leave Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> to explain his own Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Surely he could not but know, I having ſo expreſly declared my ſelf in that matter, (ſee <hi>Book</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 51.) that both in my firſt Propoſition, and the whole uſe I make of that Covenant eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed with <hi>Abraham,</hi> for the eſtabliſhing the Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, I ſtill look upon it as the conditional Covenant of Grace, or the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as conditionally made.</p>
            <p>Now then having ſeen wherein we agree, let us ſee how ſubſtantially either this my firſt Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or the uſe I make of that <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. for the Ends mentioned, is by all that Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> hath ſaid, confuted. And <hi>in Confultationem,</hi> the Sum of all he hath ſaid amounts but to this, <hi>That he himſelf and ſome others, both Paedobaptiſts and Antipaedo-baptiſts, have ſuch a ſence and underſtanding of the abſolute or ſingle Covenant of Grace, as that it admits not any
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:60484:60"/>Infants (as ſuch) to have an Intereſt in it.</hi> But how either my <hi>Propoſition,</hi> or any Uſe I make of that Scripture, ſhould be concerned in any Man's ſence or underſtanding of a Covenant, I neither intend, nor have any reſpect unto, or at leaſt of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace, as falling under another Notion than that I conſider'd it under, I ſhall leave to you and all other Men, to judg and determine as you and they ſee meet. But ſuppoſe Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> and thoſe others he mentions, ſhould ſpeak of one and the ſame Covenant, or of the Covenant under one and the ſame Notion that I do, what a ſlender Confutation of my <hi>Propoſition</hi> is it to tell us, <hi>that he and ſome others have a different underſtanding of that Covenant from what I have?</hi> And yet this it ſeems muſt go for a <hi>Confutatio,</hi> yea, a <hi>rational Confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my Book.</hi> But who knew not that thoſe who deny Infant-Baptiſm have a different ſence and underſtanding of the Covenant of Grace than what I have, before Mr. <hi>D'Laun's</hi> Papers ſaw the Light?</p>
            <p>And if any ſhall ſay, Though it is true, what Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> here ſaith is no ſufficient Confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, either of my firſt <hi>Propoſition,</hi> or of the Uſe I make of this Covenant, ſeeing what he ſaith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns a <hi>diſtinct Covenant,</hi> or the Covenant as conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered under a <hi>different Notion</hi> from that Covenant that I make uſe of for the eſtabliſhing the Practice of Infant-Baptiſm, or the <hi>Notion</hi> under which I conſider it; yet take the Covenant in that ſence that I do, and Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> (when he comes to vindicate Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>) hath proved that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not Infants; So in his 18th Page, and he ſeems to have proved it by two Reaſons.</p>
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:60484:61"/>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe he can find that Covenant to be no other than this, that <hi>he that believes ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly. Becauſe the Covenant of Grace (he ſpeaks of the <hi>conditional Covenant</hi>) gives what it requires, and enables the Covenanters to perform the Condition required, which cannot be affirmed that it doth to Infants while ſuch.</p>
            <p>In reference whereunto I ſhall only ſay, that neither of theſe Reaſons is a ſufficient Proof. For as for the firſt,</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Fault is in Mr. <hi>D'Laune;</hi> would he ſearch the Scriptures, and open his Eyes to the Light held forth from them, he may eaſily ſee the Covenant, as thus conſider'd, may, yea, doth take in Infants with their Parents.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As to his other Reaſon, It amounts to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more nor leſs than if he had ſaid, <hi>The Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant as conditional concerns not Infants, becauſe it is an abſolute Covenant.</hi> To ſay, <hi>the conditional Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant gives what it requires,</hi> is of a like import as if it ſhould be ſaid, <hi>the abſolute Covenant requires Conditions.</hi> But would Mr. <hi>D'Laune</hi> have attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what (I ſuppoſe) he hath read, he might have ſeen how Infants may be in the <hi>conditional Covenant,</hi> and yet never be enabled to perform the Conditions of it, and yet that not from any failure on God's part in his Promiſes. See my firſt Book, <hi>pag.</hi> 49, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 208, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See alſo my Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, <hi>pag.</hi> 88.</p>
            <p>Now then, Brethren, whether Mr. <hi>D'Laune</hi> hath rationally rejected my firſt Propoſition, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed that, or the Uſe I make of the Covenant
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:60484:61"/>entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> I ſhall freely leave to your, as well as all other Mens Judgments, and proceed to his Confutation of my other two Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>As to his pretended Confutation of my ſecond ſubordinate Propoſition, I ſhall freely leave it at the Bar of your, yea, of all Mens Conſciences, to determine, whether what he hath ſaid carries the leaſt real appearance of ſuch a Confutation as he pretends unto. Nay, I dare appeal to any Man of a competent underſtanding, whether what I have ſaid for the proof of this ſecond Propoſition may not be much more juſtly accounted an Anſwer to, and Confutation of his Suggeſtions, than what he hath ſaid accounted a Confutation of my Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Alas! what hath he ſaid? for whereas I had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this ſecond Propoſition four ways, he only takes notice of the laſt. And whereas I had quoted ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Texts of Scripture, from all which, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together, and mutually explaining each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I had drawn five Concluſions, the three firſt of which I had inſiſted more eſpecially upon by way of Proof, as making more directly to the proof of this Propoſition; he wholly waves thoſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and the Reaſons by which I had confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and only cites the Scriptures themſelves, and that without the leaſt notice of their mutual Aſpect one upon another, and gloſſes upon them ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally as he ſees meet and that in a direct oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to what I had evidenced to be the Mind of the Holy Ghoſt in them.</p>
            <p>Indeed he ſets down one of my Concluſions, but how wretchedly he wreſts my ſence and meaning in it, will appear to any that will read what be faith, and turn to my firſt Book, pag. 124. and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:60484:62"/>to my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> pag. 113. Alas Brethren! can you think your Cauſe can be long upheld by ſuch ſhufling, yea, and I may ſay, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt dealing; But to haſten.</p>
            <p>As to what Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> hath ſaid either for the Confutation of this ſecond, or my third ſubordinate Propoſition, I have only this further to ſay, My Books, as well as what he hath ſaid either in this Sheet, or in his Reply to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> are extant, and may be compared together; which in caſe any ſhall neglect to do, their Oppoſition to this part of the Counſel of God that concerns the Baptiſm of Infants, ſuppoſing them drawn thereinto, or eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd therein by any thing Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> hath ſaid, will be juſtly charged upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>But to proceed and touch upon Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi>'s Vindication of Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> and at the very en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance he thus expreſſes himſelf, <hi>Where I ſhall have occaſion to inlarge (where it is meet) by way of Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Mr.</hi> Hutchinſon<hi>'s Animadverſions upon this (I ſuppoſe it ſhould be) his ſecond Book,</hi> meaning my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danvers:</hi> but the truth is, he is ſo far from inlarging, that he offers not one word or ſyllable by way of Vindication of his Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions upon that Book; ſave only that in the Cloſe he reflects upon (not without ſome ſeverity) ſome (as he judges) harſh Paſſages uſed by me with reſpect to Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> of which more anon, and conſequently has left Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi> utterly deſtitute of any Relief by theſe Animadverſions. What he ſaith to my Poſtſcript is meerly to vindicate Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>'s Treatiſe of the Covenant, from thoſe Reaſons I gave therein, why I judged it utterly uſeleſs as to the Deſign carried on in it. And how
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:60484:62"/>meanly he has done it too, will ſoon appear. For whereas I gave three Reaſons why I judged it ſo; as, (1.) Becauſe he proceeds upon ſuch groſs Miſtakes about the Ground we lay for the Covenant-Intereſt, Church-Memberſhip, and Baptiſm of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. (2.) Becauſe he aſſumes and takes for grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, without any ſhew of Proof, ſeveral things, which he knew or might have known were denied by us. (3.) Becauſe his Treatiſe labours under ſuch ſad Confuſion, and that attended with ſeveral Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Contradictions. And I gave ten Inſtances to make good what I affirm of, and charge his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe with, in thoſe Reaſons. He only ſingles out four of them, and conſequently leaves his Book juſtly chargeable with all thoſe things that I aſſign of its Uſeleſneſs; though ſuppoſing Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> had fully vindicated him in reſpect of thoſe four Inſtances he takes notice of, it would not be ſo in reſpect of ſo many as I gave. And in reſpect of thoſe Inſtances he takes notice of: as for two of them he has no other way to vindicate Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> but by meer falſhood, thus in his firſt and laſt. Let what he ſaith <hi>pag.</hi> 15. ten firſt lines, be compared with my Book, and it will be found that in none of thoſe Pages ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him there is any mention of the Relation of the Infant-Seed of Believers unto <hi>Aaraham,</hi> except only in the laſt, nor any one word giving the leaſt Ground to ſuppoſe that I ground my Plea for their Intereſts in the Covenant or Baptiſm upon that their Relation; the whole Deſign of my Book is of another Import. And even in that <hi>pag.</hi> 262, the laſt Page cited by him, where I mentioned that their Relation, I expreſly ſay, <hi>That in the application of Baptiſm to them, we have a direct and primary reſpect
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:60484:63"/>to their State, as Joint-Subjects with their Parents of the Promiſes of the Covenant.</hi> It is true, I add that, <hi>Look what reſpect we have to the Myſtical Relation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents to</hi> Abraham, <hi>in the Application of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm to them; the ſame reſpect we have to the Myſtical Relation of their Infant-Seed to him, in the Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Baptiſm unto them.</hi> But my meaning is plainly only this, that it is both Parents and Childrens Intereſt in the Covenant and Promiſes, that gives them Right to, and is the Ground upon which we apply Baptiſm the preſent Token of the Covenant to them; though we own and acknowledge both to ſtand alike related to <hi>Abraham</hi> as his Seed; but it is not their Relation unto <hi>Abraham</hi> that we <hi>ground</hi> their Baptiſm upon, that is their Covenant-Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. So that do they ſtand related to <hi>Abraham</hi> or no, which is wholly another Queſtion, yet ſeeing they have an Intereſt in the Covenant, they ought to have the Token of it applied to them. So that I had juſt cauſe to charge Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> with that Miſtake, and ſo far as he proceeds thereon, his Book muſt needs be utterly uſeleſs; and yet <hi>ex abundanti</hi> in that very place in my Poſtſcript to Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> I do expreſly own that their Relation to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſhew the Inſufficiency of his Reaſonings againſt that Ground. Suppoſe we had pleaded for their Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm from it, which we do not, which Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> takes no notice of, and yet has the Confidence as though we had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed argued from it, and I had ſaid nothing for our Juſtification againſt Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> in caſe we had run into an impertinent Diſcourſe about <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>'s Seed; and as impertinently talks of a Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on worth my Reſolution, which had he read my
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:60484:63"/>
               <hi>Eſſay,</hi> he might have ſeen already reſolved. So again in the laſt Inſtance, in reſpect of which he attempts Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>'s Vindication, <hi>pag.</hi> 20. Let Mr. <hi>D'Laun,</hi> or any one elſe, ſhew where I charge Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> with any ſuch Abſurdity as he there ſaith, I do and ſhall acquit him of Falſhood in this matter. So that Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>'s Book remains utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vindicated, in reſpect of eight of thoſe ten Inſtances I gave to ſhew the Uſeleſsneſs and Inſignificancy of it, as to the End deſigned in it. And as for thoſe other two Inſtances, with reſpect to which Mr. <hi>De-Laun</hi> may ſeem to have ſaid ſomething for his vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication; yet if his Words be well look'd into, they will be found of no uſe for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For, as for the one of them, he plainly grants what I charge him with, only attempts his Relief another way, which is no Vindication at all of Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for the other, which concerns the Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities and Confuſion Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi>'s Book labours under; how has he vindicated him by falling into a double Abſurdity himſelf? (1.) In ſaying the Covenant of Grace, in reſpect of its Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is a Covenant of Works. (2.) In implying that whatever adminiſters to the Covenant of Grace (for upon that Suppoſition he muſt go, or his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> ſignifies nothing) may be called its Adminiſtration; than which what can be more abſurdly ſpoken is not eaſy to imagine: but that is all Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> has to ſay for Mr. <hi>Hutchin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> and whether he has not left his Book as he found it, be your ſelves Judges. Indeed, had Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> ſaid, That as under the firſt Teſtament the Old Covenant did; ſo under the New-Teſtament the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:60484:64"/>New Covenant does ſubſerve or adminiſter to the Covenant of Grace properly ſo called, he had poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly hit upon a Truth of no ſmall Importance for the right underſtanding the various Covenants God has made with Men.</p>
            <p>But to have done. As to what Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> ſaith concerning my denying that I call Mr. <hi>Danvers</hi>'s Book all Forgery, which he inſinuates to proceed from weakneſs of Memory, you ſhall be my Judges whether I had not reaſon ſo to do, and whether my ſo doing argues any weakneſs of Memory or no; ſurely had I called it all Forgery, Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> would have produced my words, which he cannot do. It is true, ſome have thought I was over-ſharp in ſome Paſſages in that book, to whom I have two things to ſay:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That (as Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> apologizing for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf expreſſes it Error cannot be diſputed againſt without giving it its Name; and its Abetters cannot, be reproved and admoniſhed but in words accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modating to their Miſtakes; which inded is not railing, but plain-dealing. If this be a ſufficient Apology for Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> why not for me?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The true Reaſon why I did expreſs my ſelf in more ſharpneſs than is uſual for me to do; was, that I might have engaged either Mr. <hi>Danvers,</hi> or ſome other learned Antipaedo-baptiſts, in a thorow examination of the Arguments, I had both in my firſt Book, and occaſionally in that Anſwer, offered for the eſtabliſhment of the Practice of Infant-Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. I knew the way of my Procedure was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what different from what others had gone before me in; and I concluded that a thorow Examination of my Arguments might be greatly uſeful, either for
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:60484:64"/>the detection of my Miſtakes, ſuppoſing I had lain under any, or for the farther eſtabliſhing of the Practice I pleaded for. A rational Logical Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (as I had expreſſed my ſelf) in the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the chief Grounds I had laid down, would have been exceeding welcom unto me, and I judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that ſuch quickning Expreſſions might have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged ſome body in that Service.</p>
            <p>I have only thus much more to add, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> again and again inſinuate, as though I had only dictated, and not added any thing for proof of my Poſitions and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, I ſhall appeal to your Conſciences whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſo or no, and challenge Mr. <hi>D'Laun,</hi> yea, or any other,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To produce any one Poſition or Aſſertion wherein the Cauſe of Infant-Baptiſm is concerned, that I have laid down without proof, yea, and that when it can rationally have been judged to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, by Arguments laid down and proſecuted ſyllogiſtically.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To inſtance in any one Argument or Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that is offered and raiſed againſt our Judgment and Practice by Mr. <hi>Tombs</hi> in the third Part of his Review, or any where elſe, or any other, that I have not either expreſly anſwered, or at leaſt may not receive a juſt and full Anſwer from what I have ſaid in the one or the other of thoſe Tracts I have made publick.</p>
            <p>To inſtance in any one of all thoſe Arguments I have laid down, that either Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> or Mr. <hi>D'Laun,</hi> or any one elſe, have ſo much as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to ſhew the weakneſs and invalidity of. And ſure all Men muſt needs conclude it is a ſtrange
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:60484:65"/>Confutation of Books when there is not any one Argument that is laid down from firſt to laſt, the invalidating or weakning of which has been ſo much as attempted. For Men to cry out of dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, when they know in their Conſciences that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is affirmed but what is proved, and that by ſuch Arguments as they dare not undertake to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſignifies but little. Surely I may do with ſuch Confutations and Animadverſions, as <hi>Job</hi> profeſſes he would have done with any Book his Adverſaries ſhould have written againſt him, <hi>viz. take them upon my Shoulder, and bind them as a Crown to me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, <hi>Reverend and beloved Brethren,</hi> Bear with me, though I take the boldneſs earneſtly to inteat and beſeech you, having laid aſide all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipations and Prejudices, yea, all ſuperfluity of naughtineſs, yet once again ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly to receive,<note place="margin">Eſt aliquid ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Deos, &amp; adeſſe putare. <hi>Ovid.</hi>
               </note> and in the fear of God our Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, throughly ponder the Arguments, that have been both by by others and my ſelf (which in part are here again in Love, and I hope I may ſay in a Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, preſented to you) for your ſatisfaction, and chuſe rather to become victorious Captives unto Truth, than to lie under the Charge of <hi>holding faſt Deceit, and refuſing to return.</hi> It is true, you have given us ſome account why you cannot receive that for Truth which we judge to be ſo, but I can hardly think (bear with my plainneſs) but upon a ſerious Review your ſelves muſt needs own it to be unſatisfactory. I doubt not but you have weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again and again the Arguments pleaded by ſome
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:60484:65"/>on the behalf of our Judgment and Practice, drawn from the Covenant: But let me ſay, Have not ſome Miſtakes, which ſince have been diſcovered and rectified, occaſioned your rejection of them? For my own part I muſt ſay, had not I evidently ſeen a way to rectify thoſe Miſtakes, if I had not been in your Tents, I ſhould not have abode in your oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite's with any conſiderable ſatisfaction to my ſelf. Had it been ſo indeed as ſome have thought, that the Covenant entred with <hi>Abraham</hi> had taken in all his Poſterity, at leaſt deſcending by <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> during the Firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtration, meerly as ſuch, I could not but have judged it a very rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Suppoſal, that that had been a Priviledg pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar to himſelf, and not continued to all believing Parents; or could I not have maintained the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant-Intereſt of the Infant-Seed of Believers, but by diſtinguiſhing of the Covenant as Internal and External, I ſee not how I could upon any ſolid Grounds have maintained it. Or did the Covenant only convey unto them External Priviledges, as the Ground upon which their Covenant-Intereſt and Baptiſm are pleaded upon, would have appeared to me leſs ſure and firm; ſo I ſhould have ſomewhat haeſitated whether the Advantages redounding to them, at leaſt in reſpect of thoſe that die in their Infancy, would countervail the Inconveniences of a Conteſt thereabout. Or had it been ſo that that grand Promiſe of the Covenant, wherein God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to be a God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, had (as ſimply and abſolutely conſidered) included all Spiritual Good, and conſequently that all that have an actual Intereſt in that Promiſe, muſt needs either <hi>de preſenti</hi> actually have, or <hi>de futuro</hi> be infallibly
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:60484:66"/>aſſured of ſaving Grace, I ſhould have judged it at leaſt very probable that the Covenant might be reſtrained to the Elect; or yet could I not have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed Infants, as ſuch, an other Intereſt in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, than a viſible ſtanding under the out ward Adminiſtration of it, I ſhould have readily granted they had indeed no Intereſt at all in it, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently not to be baptized. But I am fully ſatisfied theſe things are meer Miſtakes, it is quite otherwiſe. And hence not only that the Infant-Seed of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers are in Covenant, but the Conſiſtency of their being ſo with all thoſe Orthodox Doctrines main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained both by you and us againſt the <hi>Arminians,</hi> with the very great Benefit and Advantage they have thereby, appears with ſo much plainneſs and evidence to me, that I can hardly forbear to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they ſhould not do ſo to all others, who have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to any Competency of Ability for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring one Scripture with another. And though I ſuppoſe ſome of you may ſay ſomewhat more to purpoſe, than any of thoſe, who ſince theſe Miſtakes have been rectified, and our Practice truly founded upon its right Baſis, have appeared in favour of your Cauſe, have ſaid: Yet let me ſay, I verily believe they will never be able to anſwer, either ſome of thoſe Arguments Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has laid down for the Church-Memberſhip of the Infant-Seed of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or that I have offered for the eſtabliſhing of their Covenant-Intereſt and Right to Baptiſm thereupon. So as that a tender Conſcience reſiding in a Heart, <hi>from whom God has not hid <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> can quietly acquieſce therein. As for thoſe two who have concerned themſelves in my poor En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to let in ſome further Light into this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:60484:66"/>let your Conſciences ſpeak out, Did you ever read ſuch inſignificant Animadverſions and Confutations, neither the one nor the other at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting in the leaſt to ſhew the Inſufficiency of any one Argument I have laid down? ſurely neither could the Authors: nor can you ſuppoſe that ſuch Diſcourſes can yeild any other Advantage to your Cauſe than this, <hi>viz.</hi> that although they ſignify no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to thoſe that read them, yet will give riſe to a general Rumour that ſuch a book is anſwered. And alas! how are they forced, that what they ſay may carry ſome appearance of a Reply to our Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to feign us to uſe other mediums, or to <hi>argue</hi> quite otherwiſe than indeed we do, and impoſe upon us ſuch Conceſſions as we are no way obliged to, but do expreſly reject.</p>
            <p>As to the former, in reſpect of which your ſelves are not wholly innocent, how evident is it both in that Suppoſal of Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon,</hi> juſtified by Mr. <hi>D'Laun,</hi> that the main Ground we lay or can lay, to the Church-Memberſhip and Baptiſm of the Infant-Seed of Believers, is their Relation to <hi>Abraham</hi> as his Seed; and alſo that Suppoſal, that I argue from the Analogy Baptiſm bears with Circumciſion, which is apparently falſe, and is expreſly diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me. It is the Command to keep the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that I argue from, and only mention Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion to ſhew that by <hi>Covenant</hi> is there meant the Token of the Covenant.</p>
            <p>As for the latter, take two Inſtances at preſent, Both Mr. <hi>Hutchinſon</hi> and Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> will needs ſuppoſe and ſeem to think, that we muſt grant that that Covenant entred with <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 17. was the Old Covenant, ſaid by the Apoſtle to be vaniſhed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:60484:67"/>away. 2dly. That that Covenant did reach unto, and take in all <hi>Abraham</hi>'s natural Poſterity, meerly as ſuch, during the Firſt-Teſtament-Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Both which things we abſolutely deny.</p>
            <p>And that exceſſive Wrong done to ſeveral wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Antipaedobaptiſts in wreſting and perverting their Writings in favour of your Practice, is an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the ſame Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Brethren, theſe things ought not to be ſo, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (could the Aſſerters of your Practice give any rational Reply to our Arguments without the help of ſuch Artifices) would they be ſo. Can you anſwer our Arguments? ſpare us not, but do not feign us to argue from ſuch Topicks, and after ſuch a manner as we do not. If any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipaedo-baptiſts have written any thing that really countenances your Cauſe, let their words be can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly produced, but wreſt not their words, whoſe <hi>Owners abhorred <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion with your Aſſemblies,</hi> to ſuch a ſence as they never intended, nor will their words juſtly bear. But Brethren, did the Supportation of your Judgment and Practice only enforce thoſe that engage therein thus to deal with us, it might be more eaſily paſſed over. But alas! how do they injure even the Holy Ghoſt himſelf, partly by openly contradicting the expreſs letter of his holy <hi>Oracles.</hi> Thus to deny that God in that Promiſe <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. intended <hi>Abraham's</hi> natural Childen, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular thoſe that immediatly proceded from his own Loins, as ſome do; or to affirm that that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was the Covenant of Works, which Believers are now dead unto; or to deny the Continuation of that Promiſe to believing Gentiles, and that in the ſame extent in which it was given to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:60484:67"/>as a believing Parent of natural Children: What is it but to ſay to the Holy Ghoſt, as they to the Prophet, <hi>thou ſpeakeſt falſly?</hi> Let that <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. be compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14, 17, 29. Partly by impoſing upon his words ſuch a ſence as which himſelf hath no-where elſe uſed them in, and that in a direct oppoſition to that ſence he uſually and frequently hath uſed them in; ſo in reſpect of that <hi>Luk,</hi> 19.9. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Partly by charging him with ſuch impertinent Probations of his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, and Enforcements of his Exhortations, as Men of common Capacities are not ordinarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident unto: thus in reſpect of that <hi>Acts</hi> 16.31. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. Neither can the Covenant-Intereſt of the Infant-Seed of Believers be rejected without at leaſt a ſeeming Reflection upon the grace and Love of God, that he ſhould utterly conceal from his People what becomes of their Infant-Seed, who are cropt off in the Bud, before they have arrived to a Capacity of refuſing the Evil, and chuſing the Good; as in eaſe the Covenant ſecures not their ſuture ſtate (which in caſe it reaches them not, it cannot do) he has undoubtedly done.</p>
            <p>As to that Suppoſition, that the Covenant is made with the Elect, it is a meer Miſtake, as I conceive may be undeniably demonſtrated from thoſe Reaſons among others that Mr. <hi>D'Laun</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to prove that Infants cannot be concerned in it. And if you ſhall ſay, <hi>As for our own parts we deny not their Covenant-Intereſt, it is their Baptiſm we deny.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me ſay, brethren, It would be the Joy of our Hearts to underſtand that it were ſo indeed. But pray deal plainly, let not your Auditors and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:60484:68"/>lowers be kept in the dark, either expreſly own and aſſert it, or expreſly deny it. And if you do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed own it, let theſe Arguments, offered to prove the Rightfulneſs of their Baptiſm upon that Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, be throughly weighed; the Addition of more, till the Inſufficiency of thoſe he ſhewed, is unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And there is yet one thing more that I would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind you of, though thereby I am forced <hi>renovare dolorem;</hi> for I am perſwaded you do obſerve it, and the obſervation of it is a vexation to your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Souls; I mean the variety of Errours, yea, and Hereſy, found (I fear it may be ſaid without and <hi>Hyperbole</hi>) with the Generality of thoſe who as to this Practice walk in the ſame ſteps with you; yet I ſhall rather refer you to your own obſervation, and ſuch as you can credit, and in part clear Mr. F. than become your Informant my ſelf. But ſure you can conclude no leſs than that either too many of your Perſwaſion are, if not Men of corrupt Minds, yet but Children, and ſubject to be toſſed to and fro by every wind of Doctrine, or elſe that Divine Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure antedates the Judgment of the great Day, inviſibly recompenſing Deceit with Vanity. Either of which, eſpecially the latter, ſuppoſing they muſt, as (to ſpeak plainly) I am much perſwaded they ought to be aſcribed thereunto, calls aloud, as to all Men, not to enter into your Paths, ſeeing what befalls others may befall them, without great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation, Prayer, and utmoſt Search of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and yet at laſt ſuppoſing them to be ſatisfied that that is the way they ſhould walk in, to do it with a holy fear and trembling, ſo that you do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiw your Grounds again and again, and be ſure
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:60484:68"/>you can ſatisfy your Conſciences in your perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency therein, before him who will judge without <hi>reſpect of Perſons.</hi> Seeing then they are in part chargeable upon you, your owning and defending that Opinion and Practice, thus viſibly purſued with Divine Puniſhments and Judgments, having no ſmall Intereſt in the prevailing thereof among Men, and <hi>Cauſa Cauſae,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Brethren, There are ſeveral other things I could willingly have ſaid to you; but theſe things I judg neceſſary to ſet before you, partly as matter of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, and partly as Motives, yet once again with all ſeriouſneſs to review this Controverſy ſo long depending between us. And remember, that not only your ſelves, but God our Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, his Church and People, with the Souls of not a few Infants, eſpecially of ſuch whoſe Months are limited to Immaturity of Age, are neerly concerned in the Review you make, and the Reſolutions you thereupon fix in. As for our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Practice, this <hi>Quietes vivit adhuc, Chriſtus manet inſuperabile verum.</hi> As for you, in reviewing this Controverſy, and fixing your Reſolutions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, let me beſeech you to keep in mind what your ſelves perfectly know, <hi>vsz.</hi> That Conſcience is <hi>Res delicata,</hi> it cannot lie with eaſe as <hi>Job</hi>'s Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan can, when ſharp-pointed things are ſtrew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under it; and beſides it may, and often does, record ſuch things as at preſent it does not ſenſibly diſcover any offence at.</p>
            <p>I ſhall add no more, ſave only to beg your Pardon for my plainneſs, and commend you to God, and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:60484:69"/>the Word of his Grace, in ſpecial that good Word uttered by our Lord Chriſt himſelf in that <hi>John</hi> 16.13. and aſſure you, I am ſincerely yours, to ſerve you in all Offices of Chriſtian Love to my power.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH WHISTON.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="by_the_same_author">
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Author hath treated more largly on this Subject in three Books, entituled,
<list>
                  <item>I. Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men. The firſt Part.</item>
                  <item>II. Infant-Baptiſm from Heaven, and not of Men; the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Part; being an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Danver</hi>'s Treatiſe of Baptiſm.</item>
                  <item>III. An Eſſay to revive the Primitive Doctrine of Infant-Baptiſm, in the Reſolution of four Queſtions.
<list>
                        <item>1. What are the reaſons of God's appointing the Token of the Covenant to be applied to the Infant-Seed of his People?</item>
                        <item>2. What is the Good or Benefit they receive thereby?</item>
                        <item>3. What is the Duty of parents towards their Children, as bearing the Token of the Covenant?</item>
                        <item>4. What is the Improvement that Children, as grown up to years of maturity, may and ought to make of their Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm?</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All three ſold by <hi>Jonathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
